<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The epicures fast: or: A short discourse, discouering the licenciousnesse of the Romane Church in her religious fasts. By Henrie Mason, parson of St. Andrews Vndershaft, London</title>
            <author>Mason, Henry, 1573?-1647.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 145 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07207</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17608</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112435</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847689</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847689</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12743</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07207)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12743)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1074:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The epicures fast: or: A short discourse, discouering the licenciousnesse of the Romane Church in her religious fasts. By Henrie Mason, parson of St. Andrews Vndershaft, London</title>
                  <author>Mason, Henry, 1573?-1647.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 58, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G[eorge] P[urslow] for Iohn Clarke, and are to be sold at his shop, vnder St. Peters Church in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Also issued as part 2 of his: Christian humiliation .. Whereunto is added The epicures fast, 1627.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fasts and feasts --  Catholic Church --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12743:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12743:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE EPICVRES FAST: <hi>OR:</hi> A SHORT DISCOVRSE, DISCOVERING THE LICENCIOVS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ROMANE Church in her <hi>religious FASTS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> HENRIE MASON, Parſon of St. <hi>Andrews Vnderſhaft, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>G. P.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Clarke,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop, vnder St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1626.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12743:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12743:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, <hi>Dr.</hi> IOHN KING, one of the Canons of <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and ſecond Sonne to the worthy Prelate, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. KING, late Biſhop of LONDON. (<g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>)</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Good Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Did heeretofore offer to your
<note n="*" place="margin">Dr. Hen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y King.</note> el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Brother a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Booke of the right <hi>vſe</hi> of Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: and now I bring vnto your ſelfe one much leſſe, of the <hi>abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> of Faſting. My intention in both is the ſame; to teſtifie towards your deceaſed FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THER,
<pb facs="tcp:12743:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>now with the Lord, my thanks, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, dutie, and whatſoeuer a Domeſticke could owe to a louing, wiſe and vertuous Lord: and withall to expreſſe, according to my power, the loue and affection which I ſhall euer beare to his ſuruiuing Poſteritie; praying alſo, that you who haue receiued from him life and being, may follow him, and, if it may be, euen exceede him in his vertues. Which intention and deſire of mine, if you ſhall pleaſe to accept of in this ſmall Treatiſe, as your Brother did in the other; I ſhall eſteeme it in you both, as a token of your Fathers continued loue vnto me in his ſucceeding Iſſue.</p>
            <p>My purpoſe in this ſmall Treatiſe is, to lay open the ſeuerall <hi>abuſes,</hi> which in theſe later yeeres haue corrupted this holy exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of faſting, and made it both odious to God, and leſſe paſſeable among men. And this I did for two cauſes. Firſt, to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh good Chriſtians, that they beware of formalitie &amp; empty ſhews in religious du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: and more eſpecially, that when they faſt, they be not like the Hypocrites of our
<pb facs="tcp:12743:3"/>time, who in ſo foule a maner haue defiled ſo good a worke. Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> I vndertooke this Diſcouerie, thereby to detect the <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition</hi> &amp; the <hi>pride</hi> of the Roman Church; in hope that ſome, euen amongſt them, may be moued to lay theſe things to heart. And firſt, for their <hi>ſuperſtition,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> that is heereby detected, that neglecting the power and vertue of a religious Faſt, and whatſoeuer hath any goodneſſe or efficacie in it, yet they doe place religion and merit in the empty name, and the bare out-ſide, which they onely haue retained. And againe for their <hi>pride,</hi> that appeareth in this, that find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many corruptions crept into their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of faſting, contrarie to the cuſtome both of Scriptures and the ancient Church, as themſelues cannot but confeſſe; yet they had rather defend their groſſe practiſes, then acknowledge that the Church of Rome can doe any thing amiſſe. Which two foule faults, as they are vſuall with that Church in other things; ſo they are palpable in this exerciſe of faſting, as will clearely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by the particulars in this enſuing
<pb facs="tcp:12743:4"/>Treatiſe. Would GOD, our ſeduced Countreymen,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.2.</note> who haue <hi>a zeale of GOD, but not according to knowledge,</hi> would heereby learne, that all are not ancient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes that carry the old name: but that the Church of Rome can retaine the titles of Antiquitie, when ſhe hath vtterly abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed the things which were afore time meant by them. And my prayer to God is for ſuch among them, as deſire to know the truth to ſaluation, that God at length will open their eyes, to diſcerne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene things that differ; and will moue their hearts to conſider how vnſafe it is for them to commit their ſoules to thoſe mens guiding, who make the corrupt practiſe of their Church, the vnqueſtionable rule of their Doctrine. And with this Prayer I end my Preface; commending my ſelfe to your loue, my labours to your acceptance, and you and all yours to GODS bleſſing and gracious protection. <hi>Iune</hi> 12. 1626.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your louing and obliged Friend, <hi>HENRIE MASON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12743:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>IN the Authorities alledged, beſide the quoting of the Bookes, Chapters, numbers, &amp;c. I haue moſt times named the leafe or page, where the words are to be found. I did it for 2. cauſes. 1. That when I ſhould haue occaſion to reuiew any Authoritie, I might with the more ſpeede be directed to the place. 2. That if there ſhould happen any error in the number of the Bookes, Chapters, &amp;c. the addition of the leafe or page might be an helpe to amend it. And becauſe the Reader may make the like benefit of theſe quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, if he chance vpon the ſame Impreſsion that I haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſed; I thought it not amiſse to ſpecifie what Edition I followed in the ſeuerall Authors: Which is, as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Ioſephi <hi>Angles</hi> Flores theologic. Qq. Part. <hi>1.</hi> in <hi>4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> Burgis. <hi>1585.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Antiquitates</hi> Liturgicae. A Booke in three tomes in <hi>8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> without the name of the Author, Printer, place or yeere: but it was licenced by Petrus Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenſis of Doway, <hi>1604.</hi> and granted with pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge to Bellerus the Doway Printer, by the Archdukes, <hi>1603.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Io. <hi>Azorij</hi> Inſtitut. part. <hi>1.</hi> Coloniae. <hi>1602.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bellarmini</hi> Controuerſiae. in fol. Pariſ. <hi>1608.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Beyerlinck.</hi> Promptuar. Moral. part. <hi>3.</hi> Colon. in <hi>8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1616.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Martin. <hi>Bonacinae</hi> Opera in folio. Lugduni, <hi>1624.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:12743:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:12743:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:12743:6"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cajetani</hi> Summula in <hi>8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> Pariſ. <hi>1539.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Caſſiani</hi> Opera in <hi>8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> Duaci, <hi>1616.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Euſeb.</hi> Hiſtor. Graecolat. in fol. Coloniae Allobro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum, <hi>1612.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Anton. <hi>Fernandes</hi> Examen Theologiae in <hi>8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon. <hi>1621.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ioan. <hi>Fileſaci</hi> Opera, in <hi>8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> Pariſ. <hi>1614.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Vincentij <hi>Filliucij</hi> Morales quaeſt. Lugduni, <hi>1622.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Barthol. <hi>Fumi</hi> Aurea armilla, <hi>8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> Lugduni, <hi>1596.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Matthaei <hi>Galeni</hi> Catecheſes in <hi>4<hi rend="sup">to</hi>.</hi> Lugd. <hi>1593.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Iac. de <hi>Graffijs</hi> Deciſiones aureae in <hi>4<hi rend="sup">to</hi>.</hi> Antwerp. <hi>1604.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Hieronymi</hi> Opera. Paris, <hi>1609.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ioan. <hi>Hofmeiſteri</hi> Loci communes, in <hi>16<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> Pariſ. <hi>1573.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hieron. <hi>Llamas</hi> Summa eccleſiaſtica in <hi>8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt. <hi>1605.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cornel. à <hi>Lapide,</hi> in Prophetas majores. Antwer. <hi>1621.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Leonar. <hi>Leffius,</hi> de Iuſtitia &amp; Iure. Antw. <hi>1612.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Guliel. <hi>Lindani</hi> Panoplia. Colon. <hi>1575.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Iodoci <hi>Lorichij</hi> Theſaurus. Friburgi. <hi>1609.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Barthel. <hi>Medinae</hi> Inſtructie Confeſſari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rum in <hi>8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> Venet. <hi>1601.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ioan. <hi>Medinae</hi> Cod. de Iejunio. <hi>4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> Brixiae. <hi>1606.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Alphon. <hi>Piſanus</hi> de Continentia &amp; Abſtinentia. <hi>8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> Colon. <hi>1579.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Valer. <hi>Reginaldi</hi> Praxis fori poenit. fol. Coloniae. <hi>1622.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Emman. <hi>Roderiquez</hi> Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma Caſuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Colon. <hi>1620.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Franc. <hi>Toleti</hi> Inſtr. Sacerd. <hi>8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> Rothomagi, <hi>1609.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Greg. de <hi>Valentia</hi> in Thomam. Venet. <hi>1608.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12743:6"/>
            <head>THE EPICVRES FAST.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr Sauiour, in his Sermon on the Mount, among other leſſons tending to Religion and an holy life, doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct his Hearers in the right vſe of Faſting.
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 6.16, 17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>When ye faſt,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>bee not as the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, of a ſad countenance: for they disfigure their faces, that they may appeare vnto men to faſt: Verily I ſay vnto you, they haue their reward. But thou, when thou faſteſt, anoynt thy head, and waſh thy face, &amp;c.</hi> In which words our Lord doth two things. 1. He giueth a <hi>Caueat,</hi> to beware of an abuſe in faſting, ſuch as the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes did defile this holy worke with; <hi>Be not as the Hypocrites, of a ſad countenance, &amp;c.</hi> And ſecondly, he giueth vs <hi>counſell</hi> to take the right way in faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>But thou, — anoynt thy head, &amp;c.</hi> According to which example of my Lord and Maſter, I did heeretofore endeuour to giue ſome <hi>rules</hi> for the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12743:7"/>right vſe of faſting; and now I am led by the ſame example, to giue <hi>warning</hi> of ſome abuſes that may defile it. For, the Scribes and Phariſes of our time, I meane the Doctors of the Church of Rome, haue by their doctrine much more corrupted this holy exerciſe, then the Scribes and Phariſes in our Sauiours time did corrupt it by their practice. And for the detection of theſe abuſes, I haue thought it requiſite to conſider of theſe two points in the Popiſh doctrine of faſting.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>How the Church of Rome doth deſcribe a Faſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>What Indulgence or liberty they giue and take, contrary to the cuſtome of Scriptures, practice of the ancient Church, and their owne rules of Faſting.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I. </hi>The Deſcription of a Faſt, giuen by Popiſh Doctors.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt point conſiderable, is, How the Church of Rome doth deſcribe a Faſt; or wherein the nature of a Faſt, according to their doctrine, doth conſiſt. The anſwere where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to is to bee fetched from their owne words and writings. And from thence for this purpoſe I note theſe 2. things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They diſtinguiſh the ſeuerall ſorts of faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that it may be knowne what kind of Faſt it is, whereof they ſpeake. So <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth;
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Accipitur vox [ieiunium] qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuor modis, &amp;c.</hi> Bellar. de bon. oper. in partie. l. 2. cap. 1. §. I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur nomen.</note> 
                  <hi>This
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12743:7"/>word [Iejunium]</hi> or a <hi>Faſt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is taken foure waies, out of which doe ariſe, as it were, foure ſorts of Faſts;</hi> 1. a <hi>ſpirituall Faſt,</hi> 2. a <hi>morall Faſt,</hi> 3. a <hi>naturall Faſt,</hi> and 4. an <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Faſt.</hi> The <hi>ſpirituall Faſt</hi> is an abſtinence from ſinne: The <hi>morall</hi> is temperance and ſobriety in dyet: The <hi>naturall</hi> is an abſtinence from all meat and drinke: And the <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> is ſuch an abſtinence as the Church doth preſcribe. And of this laſt kinde of Faſt only, is all the queſtion in this place. Thus, or to this effect, ſpeaketh <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> And to the ſame purpoſe, but more diſtinctly, ſpeaketh <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie de Valentia,</hi> another Ieſuite:
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Greg. de Valentia in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dae, Diſput. 9. q. 2. punct. 1. in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itio. pa. 1751. A.</note> 
                  <hi>The Schoole-Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>doe vſe to diſtinguiſh of foure kindes of Faſts.</hi> The firſt is called <hi>jeiunium generale, a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Faſt,</hi> which is an <hi>abſtinence from all vnlawfull pleaſures,</hi> or ſinfull delights. The ſecond is called <hi>jeiunium naturae ſeu naturale; a naturall Faſt, which conſiſteth in an vtter abſtinence from meat &amp; drinke, in the ſence that he is ſaid to be faſting, who hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken no meate or drinke at all, that day.</hi> The third kinde may be called <hi>jeiunium morale,</hi> a <hi>morall</hi> Faſt, <hi>which conſiſteth in a right and moderate vſe of meate and drinke, according to the rules of ſobrietie or tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance.</hi> The fourth kinde is <hi>jeiunium aliud quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam peculiare,</hi> a <hi>certaine peculiar kinde</hi> of faſting, <hi>which is not to be vſed of all men, nor at all times;</hi> and it <hi>conſiſteth both in a longer forbearing of meate and drinke, then the common rule of temperance doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire; and alſo in a more ſparing and ſtrict or rigid vſe of meate and drinke, then is neceſſarie by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon rules of ſobriety.</hi> And this kinde of abſtinence
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12743:8"/>
                  <hi>is moſt properly called a Faſt:</hi> and <hi>is that</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which is commended in Scriptures, and acknowledged by Caluin and Kemnitius.</hi> And <hi>when it is kept by the rule and preſcript of the Church, it is called by the Schoole-Doctors, jeiunium Eccleſiaſticum ſeu ſacrum, the Churches Faſt, or an holy Faſt.</hi> And this is it which all ſides doe meane, when they intreate or diſpute of a Chriſtian Faſt. And to like purpoſe ſpeake others of them; whom I ſhall not need to alledge: becauſe by this that hath beene ſaid out of theſe two learned Ieſuites, it is euident, what they meane by the name of a Faſt, namely this Faſt of the Church, or this peculiar and ſtraite kinde of abſtinence and faſting, as it is preſcribed and practiſed by the Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, hauing diſtinguiſhed the kindes of faſting, and thence ſingled out that which fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their purpoſe, in the next place they doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe or declare the nature of this <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> Faſt, and tell vs what are the <hi>eſſentiall</hi> or neceſſary properties of it. And for this purpoſe, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> defineth this Faſt to be
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Bellarm. de bonis oper. in partic. l. 2. c. 1. §. Ieiunium Eccleſiaſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Abſtinentia cibi, ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dùm Eccleſiae regulam aſſumpta; an abſtinence from meate, vndertaken according to the rule of the Church,</hi> or that rule, which the Church doth preſcribe to be obſerued in a Faſt. And the things required by the Churches rule, he
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ibid. §. vlt.</note> telleth vs, are three: 1. <hi>Vt qui jeiunat, ſemel tantùm in die cibum ſumat; That he who faſteth, doe take meate but once onely in the day.</hi> 2. <hi>Vt vna illa refectio ſit coena, non prandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um; that that one meale or refection be a ſupper, not a dinner.</hi> 3. <hi>Vt habeatur ciborum delectus; that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12743:8"/>there bee obſerued a choiſe of meates, eſpecially that men forbeare fleſh, when they faſt according to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Church.</hi> Thus <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> And <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> hee noteth
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Lo. citat. pag. 1753. C.</note> 3. things as <hi>eſſentiall</hi> to this Faſt: 1. <hi>Quòd per illud diutiùs quàm exigit co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munis regula temperantiae, abſtinetur à cibo; that men doe then forbeare meate longer then the common rule of tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance doth require.</hi> 2. <hi>Quòd in ipſo vſu cibi, abſtine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur à quibuſdam eſcis, &amp;c. that when men doe eate, they abſtaine from ſome certaine meates, fleſh, eggs, and milke-meates.</hi> 3. <hi>Quòd hujuſmodi abſtinentia, tum quoad diuturnitatem, tum etiam quoad ciborum qualitatem, ordinatur ad finem ipſum temperantiae, qui eſt edomatio carnis, &amp; refraenatio concupiſcentiae; that this abſtinence, both for the continuance of it, and for the quality of the meate at the end of it, bee refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ordained for the taming of the fleſh, and the bridling of luſt, that it doe not too violently withſtand reaſon.</hi> Theſe things <hi>Valentia</hi> requireth, &amp; thence frameth an eſſentiall <hi>definition</hi> of a Faſt, conſiſting on theſe three things, as the eſſentiall parts or properties of it. And <hi>Piſanus,</hi> another Ieſuite, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing with his fellowes for the ſubſtance, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth this kinde of Faſt thus;
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſt igitur ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abſtinentia quaedam arctior, qua home ab om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus cibis, aut ſaltem à quibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam lautioribus ſe abſtinet, qua et ſemel duntaxat in die, nempe poſt conſuetam pran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dtoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> horam cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus reficit</hi> Piſan. de Abſtinent. ca. 1. pa. 98.</note> 
                  <hi>It is a ſtraiter kinde of abſtinence,</hi> [to wit, then the rules of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance doe require] <hi>by which a man doth forbeare all meates, or at leaſt ſome of the finer or more dainty meates; in which abſtinence alſo he doth feede or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh his body but once onely in the day, namely, after the accuſtomed houre of dinner.</hi> Thus hee; and ſo doe others moe; who though they may vary in their manner of ſpeech, or in ſome circumſtanciall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12743:9"/>point, yet doe for the moſt part ſpeake in the like manner, of the nature of this Faſt, as theſe three Ieſuites doe.</p>
               <p>In which ſayings and Deſcriptions of theirs, I deſire the Reader to take notice of two things by the way, which being well remembred, may ſerue for further vſe hereafter.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That theſe <hi>Deſcriptions</hi> are in part ſo fitted to their owne Faſts, as that they diſagree with the Faſts both mentioned in Scriptures, and practiſed in the Primitiue Church: as when they define a Faſt to be an <hi>abſtinence from meat</hi> onely: for ſo it is vſed in the Church of Rome: but it was not ſo in the ancient Church of God. For the practice of Gods people in the Scriptures, and of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers in the Primitiue Church, was as well to forbeare drinke as meate, during the time of their abſtinence: as heereafter may appeare more fully.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That theſe Deſcriptions of a Faſt, are in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things ſo fitted to the practice of Antiquitie, that they doe condemne the Faſts of the Romane Church: as for example, When they ſay, that in an holy Faſt, men muſt haue but <hi>one refection,</hi> and that muſt be <hi>a ſupper, not a di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner;</hi> &amp; that both their <hi>abſtinence,</hi> and their <hi>choiſe of meates</hi> when they eate, muſt be ſuch, as may <hi>tame the fleſh,</hi> and <hi>bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle the luſts of it.</hi> For all theſe things are moſt true in true and ſincere Faſts, ſuch as the Scriptures doe commend, and the ancient Church did pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe; but in Popiſh Faſts they finde no place at all: as ſhall be manifeſt (God willing) in the due place.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:12743:9"/>
               <p>And the reaſon of this medley or mixture of ancient and latter cuſtomes in their definition of a Faſt, I take to be this; becauſe our new Roman Doctors doe ſo deſcribe faſting, as their elder Schoole-Doctors, <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Hales,</hi> had done before them: and theſe men did ſo deſcribe a Faſt, as the Romane Church did then practice and preſcribe it. And their cuſtome then was, to <hi>drinke</hi> at all times, but not to <hi>eate</hi> ſaue once in the day, and not ſooner then three of the clocke in the afternoone. For as for the <hi>noone-tide dinner,</hi> and the euening <hi>Collation,</hi> things now allowable in a Popiſh Faſt, they are abuſes of later times, ſince <hi>Hales</hi> and <hi>Thomas</hi> were departed this life. And this ſhall ſuffice to be ſaid of the firſt point, namely how the Romane Church doth define a religious Faſt.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <p>THe next point to be conſidered is, What In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence or liberty they take and grant, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the practice of Scriptures, cuſtomes of the ancient Church, and theſe rules of their own. And this may be conſidered or obſerued in fiue parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars: 1. In their <hi>choiſe of meates.</hi> 2. In the <hi>num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of their Refections.</hi> 3. In the <hi>time of their eating,</hi> or breaking vp of their Faſt. 4. In <hi>the quantitie</hi> of their meate and drinke. And 5. in their <hi>diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> with the Rules or Lawes of Faſting.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:12743:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II. </hi>Choiſe of meates in a Popiſh Faſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F the fiue particulars, the firſt is, their <hi>choiſe of meates.</hi> Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which, I note theſe things for the preſent purpoſe.</p>
               <p n="1">I. They doe not require in any Faſt of theirs, a <hi>totall abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence</hi> from all meate and drinke. For firſt they define
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ieiunium eſt abſtmentia quae dam ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ior, quae homo ab omnibus cibis, aut ſaltem à quibuſdam lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioribus ſe abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, &amp;c.</hi> Piſan. de Abſtinent. cap. 1. pag. 98.</note> a Faſt to be an <hi>abſtinence from all meates, or at leaſt from the more delicate or dainty meates.</hi> In which ſpeech I note two things. 1. That they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a <hi>totall abſtinence</hi> in Faſts: and therefore the Faſts in the reformed Churches are in this reſpect warrantable, <hi>euen our enemies being Iudges.</hi> 2. That in their Faſts it is held ſufficient <hi>abſtinence,</hi> if a man forbeare ſome meates, though he feede on others. Secondly, they allow men any ſort of drinke in the time of their faſting. For,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>De cibi tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, non de po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eûs abſtinentia datum eſt praecep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eum eccleſiaſticu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Reginal. prax. fori Poenitent. l. 4. num. 173. pag. 155.</note> 
                  <hi>the precept of the Church</hi> for faſting, <hi>was made and meant of abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence from meate onely, and not from drinke;</hi> ſaith <hi>Reginaldus.</hi> And <hi>Azorius,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccleſiae ieiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niun eſt, quo non à potione, ſed à cibo abſtinemus.</hi> Azor. Inſtit. part. 1. l. 7. c. 8. pa. 555. 1. Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph. Angles Flor. in 4. Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, part. 1. de Iejunio, q. 9. Difficult. 2. pag. 433. Alij<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> paſſim.</note> The Faſt of the Church</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is that, in which wee doe abſtaine, not from drinke, but from meate.</hi> And by this it appeareth, that they do not require a <hi>totall abſtinence</hi> in their Faſts, either from all meates, or from any drinke.</p>
               <p n="2">II. They doe allow of <hi>wine, hot waters,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other ſtrong drinkes on their faſting day. So
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12743:10"/>
                  <hi>Azorius</hi> ſaith,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Conſentiens eſt opinio, potion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> vini, fiue manè ante prandium, ſiue poſt prandi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> veſperè ieiunium non ſoluere.</hi> Azo. Inſtit. part. 1. l. 7. c. 10. q. 7. pag. 562.</note> 
                  <hi>It is an vniforme opinion of Diuines and Canoniſts, that the drinking of Wine, whether it be in the morning before dinner, or after dinner in the euening, doth not breake a mans faſt.</hi> And ſo ſay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo: but it will be needleſſe to alledge them, ſeeing the Ieſuite ſaith, that it is an opinion, in which they generally agree.</p>
               <p n="3">III. They allow <hi>Electuaries</hi> and <hi>ſpices,</hi> and whatſoeuer elſe doth principally ſerue to helpe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, or to further digeſtion. So <hi>Leſsius</hi> ſaith,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Inſertur ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundò non probi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beri vſum Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuariorum &amp; conditerum, &amp;c.</hi> Leſſ. de Iuſt. &amp; Iure, l. 4. c. 2. nu. 10. pag. 719.</note> that the vſe of <hi>Electuaries</hi> and <hi>condited</hi> things is not forbidden in the time of a Faſt. And <hi>Reginal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> hauing ſaid that a man breaketh not his Faſt by drinking, addeth,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Nec etiam frangitur ſumpts one Electuarioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, niſi ſumantur in fraudem ieiunij.</hi> Reginald. l. 4. nu. 173. pa. 155. v. Bellar. de Ieiun. cap. 1. pag. 168, 169.</note> 
                  <hi>Neither is the Faſt broken by taking of Electuaries.</hi> And becauſe no man ſhould be ignorant how farre they ſtretch the vſe of this word, he ſaith, they meane by it,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>N̂ec itêm E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuariae. Quo nomine Palud. ipſe quid intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat, exprimit his verbis; Dico an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem omnia buiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi, quae conſis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euerunt, ſicut ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, ſumi poſt prandium ad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uandam digeſtionem, &amp;c.</hi> Reginald. l. 4. num. 152. pag. 151.</note> 
                  <hi>all manner of things which are vſed, as ſpices are, to bee eaten after meales, to helpe digeſtion.</hi> And to like purpoſe <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus Angles,
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ea, quae per modum medicinae tradiſolent, quanquam ſaepe accipiantur, Eccleſiae ieiunium minime ſoluunt. Haec con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſio intelligitur non ſolum de ſyrupis &amp; pharmacis, verum etiam de quibuſcun<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> alijs condime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> &amp; Electuarijs, quae verè per modum medicinae aſſumu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, &amp;c.</hi> Ioſeph. Angles in 4. Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. part. 1. q. 9. art. 2. Difficult. 3. pag. 434.</note> Thoſe things</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which are giuen by way of medicine, though they bee often taken</hi> on a faſting day, <hi>doe not breake the Faſt of the Church.</hi> He addeth, that <hi>this Concluſion is not only meant of ſyrups and phyſicall druggs, but alſo of all other preſerued things and electuaries, which are truly taken by way of medicine.</hi> Beſides, in their Faſts, they ſay, that <hi>abſtinence from meate</hi> onely is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, not from <hi>drinke nor medicine.</hi> And what they meane by theſe words, they explaine in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12743:11"/>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Id quod prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipaliter inſtitutu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt ad nutritione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, dicitur cibus: — id verò quod principaliter facit ad bonam nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti diſpoſitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> &amp; ciborum digeflionem, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catur potus: &amp; id quod principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter eſt contra morbos,—voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur medicina.</hi> Reginald. l. 4. nu. 125. p. 147.</note> 
                  <hi>That which is principally ordained for nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment, that is called Meate; that which is prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally for the good diſpoſition of the foode, and the digeſtion of meates, that is called Drinke; and that which is principally againſt diſeaſes and infirmities, that is called Medicine.</hi> And ſo in the concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Spicerie, Confections, Electuaries, Preſerues,</hi> and ſuch like <hi>Iuncates,</hi> commonly vſed at the end of meales, theſe they approue as lawfull and warant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able enough, without any danger of breaking their Faſt, though they bee vſed many times in one day, and without any iuſt cauſe of infirmity in the partie that taketh them: for by their doctrine, if the things ſo taken be ordinarily meant for drinke or medicine, they may lawfully bee vſed by any man, whether for this or for other ends.</p>
               <p n="4">IIII. Though
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Secunda pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitio est, in Quadrageſimali ieiunio prohibitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe non tantùm carnium vſum, ſed etiam eorum quae ex carne ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginem habent; vt lactis, butyri, caſei, ouorum: in alijs autem ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunijs, prohibitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tantùm eſſe car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium vſum.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginald. l. 4. nu. 144 pag. 150.</note> 
                  <hi>in Lent time, they forbid the vſe of eggs, cheeſe, butter, &amp;c.</hi> yet <hi>in other Faſts, the vſe of fleſh onely is forbidden</hi> by their Lawes. So <hi>Reginaldus</hi> ſaith, and he giueth this reaſon for it; becauſe <hi>non datur in lure textus, there is no Text in the Law,</hi> to forbid other meates in their ordinarie Faſts. And to like purpoſe others of them ſpeake alſo; <hi>vnleſſe</hi> (as ſome adde) <hi>the cuſtome</hi> of ſome place doe perhaps require more then the Canon of the Church doth. And ſo, when all is laid together, it is cleare, that the Church of Rome in her ordinary Faſts, doth forbid no other meate but <hi>fleſh</hi> onely; and in her ſtricteſt Faſts, alloweth the beſt <hi>wines,</hi> and the fineſt <hi>juncates,</hi> and the hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt <hi>ſpices,</hi> and whatſoeuer elſe is of the like nature. And this is it which they teach for their choiſe of meates.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:12743:11"/>
               <p>But heerein they ſwarue not a little, both from the practice of <hi>Antiquitie,</hi> and the right vſes of a <hi>religious</hi> Faſt. And firſt, that they ſwarue from the practiſe of <hi>Antiquitie,</hi> recorded as well in the Scriptures, as in the writings of the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, may appeare by theſe two conſiderations. 1. That the <hi>Ancients,</hi> during the time of their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence, did forbeare all as well <hi>drinke</hi> as <hi>meate,</hi> not allowing themſelues for that time any kinde of ſuſtenance. To this purpoſe it is that <hi>Moſes</hi> his Faſt in the Mount is thus deſcribed; <hi>He was there with the Lord fortie dayes and forty nights, hee did neither eate bread, nor drinke water. Exod.</hi> 34.28. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 9.9, 18. And ſo, when <hi>Dauid</hi> faſted for <hi>Abner, So doe God to me,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and more alſo, if I taſte bread or ought elſe till the Sunne be downe.</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.35. And when <hi>Eſther</hi> appointed the Iewes to faſt, <hi>Faſt ye for me</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>and neither cate nor drinke three daies, night nor day. Eſther</hi> 4.16. And the King of <hi>Niniueh</hi> proclaiming a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Faſt through the Citie, <hi>Let neither man nor beaſt,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>heard nor flocke taſte any thing: let them not feede, nor drinke water. Ion.</hi> 3.7. Nor can there be found any example in the Scriptures, in which any <hi>drinke</hi> was vſed or allowed during their faſting day, till euentide, when their Faſt broke vp. For as for that place of <hi>Daniel,</hi> where he ſaith of himſelfe, <hi>I was mourning three full weekes: I ate no pleaſant bread, neither came fleſh nor wine in my mouth, &amp;c. Dan.</hi> 10.2, 3. which the Doctors of Rome doe ſo frequently vrge for their <hi>choiſe</hi> of meates, it maketh nothing for the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12743:12"/>purpoſe. For <hi>Daniel</hi> did not <hi>faſt</hi> with thoſe meats, but rather <hi>broke</hi> his Faſt with them: I meane, that <hi>Daniels</hi> Faſt was a totall abſtinence from all meat and drinke for the whole day; and the courſe fare there ſpoken of, was the diet that hee vſed at night, when his dayes Faſt was ended: as I haue proued
<note n="*" place="margin">Treatiſe of Faſting, cap. 1.</note> elſe-where. And as this was the practice of holy men in Scriptures, ſo the like was the practice of religious men mentioned in anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Writers. <hi>Euſebius</hi> relating the Hiſtory of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine religious men about <hi>Alexandria</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> telleth out of <hi>Philo,</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cibum aut potionem ante ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis occaſum nemo illorum capit.</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeb. Hiſt. l. 2. c. 16.</note> that <hi>none of them did take any either meate or drinke before the Sunne ſetting.</hi> And <hi>Caſsian</hi> preſcribing rules of abſtinence for the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious men of his time,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hanc inpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis cautionem ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimet indicat, vt non potûs quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam, non oſûs vlla oblectatione deuictus, ante fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem legitima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, communem<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionis horam, extra menſam percipere ſibimet prorſus indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geat.</hi> Caſſian. Inſtitut. l. 5. cap. 20. p. 216.</note> 
                  <hi>Let euery one</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>impoſe vpon himſelfe this caution, that he doe not any way permit himſelfe to taſte any drinke or meate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſet time of faſting</hi> be accompliſhed, and <hi>the vſuall houre of feeding be</hi> come. By all which it may appeare, that the ancient cuſtome of Gods ſeruants in their Faſts was, to forbeare all, as well <hi>drinke</hi> as <hi>meate,</hi> during the time of their abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence. Secondly, It is to be conſidered, that the Ancients, when they did refreſh themſelues on their faſting daies, which was in the euening, they vſed not <hi>wines,</hi> nor <hi>ſpices,</hi> nor <hi>juncates,</hi> but courſe and vnpleaſant fare, ſuch as might at once both refreſh nature and afflict it. So <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of his diet, while the daies of his faſting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, ſaith of himſelfe,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Dan. 10.3.</note> 
                  <hi>I ate no pleaſant bread, neither came fleſh nor wine in my mouth.</hi> Where we may note, that <hi>Daniel</hi> vpon his faſting dayes ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12743:12"/>as well from <hi>ſtrong drinke</hi> and <hi>fine bread,</hi> as he did from <hi>fleſh.</hi> And therefore, as before I ſhewed that this place doth make nothing for Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh <hi>choiſe</hi> of meates; ſo heereby it appeareth, that it doth vtterly ouerthrow it. And ſo in the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Church of Chriſt, St. <hi>Hierom</hi> teaching <hi>Nepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tianus</hi> the true properties of an holy Faſt,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sint tibi pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, caſta, ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, moderata, &amp; non ſuperſtitioſa iciunia. Quid prodeſt oleo non veſci, &amp; moleſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as quaſdam diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultateſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ciboru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quaerere, caricas, piper, nuces, pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum fructus, ſimilam, mel, piflacia? Tota hortorum cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura vexatur vt cibario non veſcamur pane: et dum delicias ſectamur, à regno Coelorum retrabimur.</hi> Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. ep. 2. ad Nepotian. pa. 18. A.</note> 
                  <hi>Let thy Faſts</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>be pure, chaſte, ſincere, moderate, and not ſuperſtitious. For what auaileth it</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to forbeare oyle, and to ſeeke after farre fetched and deare bought niceties,</hi> as <hi>drie Figgs, Pepper, Nuts, Dates, Simnels, Honey, Piſtace nuts? Wel-dreſſed Gardens are tumbled ouer, that wee may not feede on browne bread: and while we follow after delicates, we are drawne backe from the Kingdome of Heauen.</hi> And if this holy Father do not allow of theſe ſo meane <hi>delicates</hi> in compariſon, how would hee thunder againſt <hi>ſweet wines,</hi> and <hi>ſweet meates, marchpanes, preſerued ſtuffe,</hi> and <hi>condited juncates,</hi> all of them very warrantable on a Romane faſting day? And this cuſtome of the ancient Church, is ſo cleare and well knowne to all that knowe any thing in Antiquitie, that the Writers of the Church of Rome doe confeſſe it to be true. The Author of the Booke called <hi>Antiquitates Liturgicae,</hi> ſaith,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Antiq. Liturg. to. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> feriâ quarta quatuor tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum. cap. 1. pag. 101.</note> 
                  <hi>[Fuit olim par ratio vini, quae carnis;] There was anciently the ſame reaſo of wine, that was of fleſh.</hi> And not long after he addeth, that the meates <hi>forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by the Canons</hi> in time of faſting, <hi>were delicate meates, either by nature, or made ſuch by Arte.
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Poſtremum à quo abſtinere inbent canones, ſunt cibi delicati, ſiue naturâ, ſiue arte conditi.</hi> Ibid. pag. 105.</note>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:12743:13"/>Lindan</hi> ſaith, that
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Jeiunia no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra, quae—dum olei ſtammas, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni aeſtum, omniſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> aromatum gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ignes Helluoni infarciunt ſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho, veteribus Chriſtianis omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no fuiſſe non mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dò incognita, ſed &amp; intolerabilia, at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> adeò abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanda, pijs omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus vetera cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantibus arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur notius, quàm vt de ea re vlla ſint verba pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundenda.</hi> Lind. Panopl. l. 3. c. 11. pag. 89.</note> 
                  <hi>Wines,</hi> and <hi>Spices,</hi> and <hi>Confecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> now familiar in their Faſts, would haue <hi>ſeemed intalerable to the ancient</hi> Church. <hi>Beyerlynck</hi> ſaith, that
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Abſtinebant illi piſcibus, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> potu, qui ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briare poteſt: nunc in ſolis car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus ciborum delectus fere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtit.</hi> Beyer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linck. prompt. in feſto Cine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, tex. 3. pag. 64.</note> 
                  <hi>they</hi> (the Ancients) <hi>did abſtaine from fiſh, and all drinke that might ouerturne the braine; but that now among them, their choiſe of meates conſiſteth almoſt in fleſh only. Reginaldus</hi> ſaith,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Licet vinum olim fuerit de nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero rerum quae in die ieiunij ſumi prohibentur, nunc tamen non eſſe.</hi> Reginald. l. 4. num. 151. pag. 151.</note> 
                  <hi>Though wine anciently was in the number of thoſe things which are forbidden on faſting dayes, yet it is not now ſo. Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaeus Galenus</hi> ſaith,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vinum vix puerperis concedebatur: ſanos autem &amp; valentes illudguſtare in Quadrageſima &amp; quartis, ſextiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> feriis, nefas fuiſſe teſtantur Epiphan. Timotheus &amp; Balſamon.</hi> Mat. Galenus Catech. 93. pag. 291.</note> 
                  <hi>Wine was ſcarce permitted to women in childe-bed: but that men in health ſhould taſte it in Lent, or on Wedneſdaies and Frydaies, was held as an hainous thing.</hi> And <hi>Piſanus,
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Veteres Canones non ſolum vinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſed etiam ſiceram interdixere, &amp; omne quod inebriare poteſt, &amp; mulſam ac ceruiſiam: olera tantum concedebant in eſum, ſeclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis etiam ipſis piſcibus.</hi> Piſan. de Abſtinent. cap. 14. pag. 162.</note> The an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Canons</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>did not onely forbid wine, but ſtrong drinke, and Meath, and Ale, and all that might ouercome the braine: they onely allowed hearbs for meate; fiſhes being forbidden alſo.</hi> And <hi>Hofmeiſter</hi> citeth a ſaying out of <hi>Theophilus Alexandrinus,</hi> that
<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Qui legum praecepta cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diunt, ignorant vinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ieiunijs, carniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſum repudiant.</hi> Hof. Loc. com. cap. 17. fol. 176. pa. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>they who keepe the rules of the Lawes, know not any wine in their Faſts.</hi> It is a cleare caſe then, that the Ancients did forbeare <hi>wine</hi> and <hi>ſtrong drinke,</hi> and <hi>pleaſant meates,</hi> when they refreſhed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vpon their faſting daies. And conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the <hi>choiſe</hi> of meates, which the Church of Rome doth make, is moſt oppoſite to the practice of Gods people in elder and purer times.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:12743:13"/>
               <p>Secondly, the <hi>choiſe</hi> that the Church of Rome doth make of her meates for a faſting day, doth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow the very vſe of a religious Faſt. For by their owne <hi>definitions</hi> and determinations, the vſe of a right Faſt is for <hi>afflicting</hi> of the body, and <hi>ſubduing</hi> of luſt, and <hi>elevating</hi> of the minde to God-ward: but their <hi>choiſe</hi> of meates ouerthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth theſe ends and vſes. For, <hi>ſpices,</hi> and <hi>ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meates,</hi> and <hi>preſerued</hi> ſtuffe, and <hi>confectionary</hi> ware, and <hi>ſtrong wines,</hi> (all which, and much more, are allowable with them in their religious Faſts: nay, they do ordinarily prouide the <hi>beſt wines,</hi> or where wines are not ſo vſuall, <hi>Braggot &amp; Meath,</hi> &amp; other choiſe drinkes, to keepe Lent Faſt withall:) theſe, I ſay, doe pleaſe nature, inflame the blood, fill the head, and prouoke luſt; ſo farre are they from helping to cleare the braine, elevate the minde, coole luſt, and afflict the body. This truth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the euidence of it in reaſon, is acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the Aduerſaries alſo. <hi>Iacobus de Graff is,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Etſi vinum ſit nutritiuum; &amp; ad concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiam magis prouocet potus vini, quàm eſus carnium,—ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, &amp;c.</hi> Iaco. de Graff. part. 1. lib. 2. c. 37. num. 24. pag. 215.</note> Although</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>wine be nutritiue</hi> or of a nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing nature, <hi>and the drinking of wine doth more prouoke men to luſt then the eating of fleſh doth; yet, &amp;c. Piſanus,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                        <hi>A quibuſdam terrae fructibus abſtinebant olim Catholici, in Quadrageſima, vt docuit Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtinus contra Fauſtum, nempo ab Aromatis, aut ijs quae venerem excitant.</hi> Piſan. de Abſtinent. cap. 14. pag. 165.</note> Catholikes</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>in times paſt, did abſtaine from ſome fruites of the earth in Lent time, as Auguſtine doth witneſſe; as namely from ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſuch things as ſtirre vp</hi> or prouoke <hi>luſt.</hi> And ſo ſpeake others: but I will content my ſelfe with one teſtimony more, and that is of <hi>Cornelius à Lapide,</hi> a late learned Ieſuite. Hee writing on theſe words of <hi>Daniel, Neither came there fleſh nor
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12743:14"/>wine in my mouth;</hi> noteth, that the
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eteres Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiani vſi ſunt Xerophagiâ</hi> .i. <hi>cibis aridis, vti teflantur Tertul. Cypr. Baſil. &amp; alij. Id<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> facieba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t triplici de cauſa. Primò, ad poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam. Sicut enim potus, quia liquidus &amp; ſubti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis &amp; penetrans intima, intimiùs ſingulas corporis partes afficit &amp; recreat; ita ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flinere à potu et à liquidis, veſci<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> aridis, maior eſt poenite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia, quàm veſci liquidis &amp; abſtinere aridis. Sis, ſitis magis affligit hominem quàm fames: ac proinde faciliùs eſt eſurienti ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinere à cibo, quàm ſitienti ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinere à potu. Secundò, ad caſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem. Cibi enim aridi arefaciunt corpus, &amp; humo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem venereum conſumunt. Tertiò, ad ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiam, ſtudiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; orationem. Qui enim liqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis abſtinet, caret vaporibus &amp; fumis, qui caput, rationem &amp; iudicium offuſcont, obſcurant &amp; bebetant. Hinc vetus dictum, Anima ſuca eſt ſapientiſſima.</hi> Corn. à Lapide in Daniel. 10.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Ancients did vſe a dry kinde of foode,</hi> (conſiſting of bread, ſalt, water, and raw rootes, and ſuch like) which they called <hi>Xerophagia,</hi> .i. a dry feeding. And <hi>they did it,</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>for three cauſes.</hi> 1. <hi>Ad paenitentiam; for an act of repentance,</hi> or (to vſe their own phraſe) <hi>for doing of penance. For, as drinke, becauſe it is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid, and of a ſubtill ſubſtance, and eaſily piercing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the inward parts, doth more affect and refreſh all the parts of the body; ſo abſtinence from drinke, and liquid things, and eating of dry foode, is a greater pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, then if a man ſhould eate moiſt things, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from dry. So, thirſt doth more afflict or chaſten a man, then hunger doth; and therfore it is more eaſie for an hungry man to forbeare meat, then for a thirſty man to forbeare drinke. Secondly,</hi> They vſed this dry feeding (ſaith he) <hi>ad caſtitatem; for preſeruing of chaſtitie. For dry meates doe dry the body, and conſume venereous moiſture. Thirdly, Adſapientiam, ſtudium &amp; orationem; for furthering of wiſdome, meditation and prayer. For hee that refraineth moiſt meates, is free from vapours and fumes, which doe darken and dull reaſon and iudgement. And hence came the old ſaying, Anima ſicca eſt ſapientiſsima; The dry ſoule is the moſt wiſe.</hi> And if this bee true, as both reaſon doth teach, and learned men of the Romane Church doe acknowledge; we haue two concluſions from hence for our purpoſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Concl.</hi> Seeing <hi>Daniel</hi> and the ancient Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, vpon good ground and reaſon, did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12743:14"/>wine and moiſt meates, and eate dry things, when they refreſhed themſelues vpon their faſting daies: therefore Papiſts, who permit all ſorts of wine, and doe vſe to chaſten the body, by filling it with ſtrong drinkes, are moſt vnlike to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men of elder times. And therefore it is an idle flouriſh, when they alledge Antiquity for the bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering vp of their <hi>choiſe of meates:</hi> the cuſtome of the Ancients being heerein no more like to the cuſtome of the preſent Romane Church, then Chalke is to Cheeſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Concl.</hi> Seeing wine and drinkes, and moiſt things, and ſpicerie wares, doe more prouoke luſt, and more dull the braine, and more refreſh and content nature, than drie meates doe: therefore Papiſts make a mad choiſe of meates; when on their faſting dayes, which ſhould ſerue for abating of luſt, and afflicting of the body, and eleuating of the minde in prayer and meditation, they allow all ſorts of wine and ſtrong drinkes; and adde to their drinkes, ſweet-meates, and conſerues and confections, and ſpices, and what elſe may either pleaſe the taſte, or content nature, ſo it bee not fleſh. Let them ceaſe then to boaſt of their <hi>morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying</hi> of the fleſh by preſcribing of many faſts: for the <hi>Drunkard</hi> and the <hi>Glutton</hi> would, to chooſe, wiſh ſuch a faſting day once or twiſe a weeke, for the ſatisfying of their appetite, as theſe men doe preſcribe and practiſe for the <hi>macerating</hi> and <hi>cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying</hi> of their fleſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:12743:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III. </hi>The number of refections allowed in a Popiſh Faſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſecond particular, wherein the libertie, or licenciouſneſſe rather, which the Romane Church doth take and vſe in her Faſts, is, the <hi>number</hi> of <hi>refections</hi> allowable with them on a faſting day. And for this purpoſe, I finde, that they allow, firſt, a <hi>ſet meale,</hi> which is their Dinner. Secondly, a <hi>little meale,</hi> which they call, <hi>Coenulam, a little Supper;</hi> and <hi>Refectiunculam,</hi> a <hi>ſmall refection;</hi> or <hi>Collationem veſpertinam,</hi> a <hi>Collation in the euening.</hi> And thirdly, they allow Drinkings all day long, as many as ye will; which we may call their continuall or all-day <hi>Beuers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for the firſt of theſe, that is, their Dinner, they acknowledge that to be a full meale; &amp; they ſay that it is the only refection which they allow vpon a faſting day. And therefore I ſhall not neede vpon this occaſion, to ſay any more of it; all that heerein I doe intend, being onely to ſhew how many refections they do allow. But for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two, they do ſo mince the matter when they ſpeake of them, as if theſe deſerued not the name of any <hi>Refreſhing</hi> or <hi>Refection.</hi> And therefore it will be requiſite to inſiſt vpon theſe a little longer: that we may ſee what they ſay, and what we may thinke of them.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:12743:15"/>
               <p n="1">1. To beginne then with the former, which is their euening <hi>Collation,</hi> or <hi>little Supper,</hi> as they call it; we may, for diſcouering of their <hi>indulgence</hi> therein, conſider three things. Firſt, the <hi>qualitie</hi> of the meate then allowed. Secondly, The <hi>quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity</hi> of it. And thirdly, the <hi>reaſon</hi> and grounds, from whence this indulgence did ariſe. In all which, that no man may thinke them to be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged wrongfully, I will deliuer their opinion in their owne words.</p>
               <p>And firſt, for the <hi>qualitie</hi> of the meate, or the kindes of things allowed by them, <hi>Azorius</hi> ſaith,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Communi iam<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſu receptu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, vt parum pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis etiam eda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, vel ſeorſim ſolum, vel vnà cum fructibus, herbis, vel alijs cibis leuioribus, cuiuſmodi ſunt fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, vua paſſa, nuces, pira, poma, vel alia ex ſac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charo vel melle confecta, vel piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciculus paruulus.</hi> Azor. Inſtit. part. 1. l. 7. cap. 8. q 7. pa. 557.</note> that <hi>the common cuſtome is,</hi> (and that both he and the reſt do approue of) <hi>for men to eate a little bread, either by it ſelfe alone, or together with fruites, hearbs, or other lighter meates, ſuch as are figgs, raiſins of the ſunne, peares, apples, or other things made of ſugar, or of honey, or a little ſmall fiſh. Filliucius</hi> ſaith,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dico omnes conuenire, quòd licitè ſumi poſſint ea, quae commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niter in ientaculis &amp; collatiunculis apponi ſolent: qualia ſunt arbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum fructus, her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bae, &amp; cibi leuio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res; vt ficus, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mygdalae, vuae paſſae, nuces, pirae, poma, oliuae, bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laria.</hi> Filliuc. Moral Qq. Tract. 27. part. 2. c. 2. num. 29. pag. 280.</note> 
                  <hi>that all doe agree, that thoſe things which commonly are brought to table at breakfaſts and banquets, may lawfully bee vſed; ſuch as are the fruites of trees, hearbes, and lighter meates, as figgs, almonds, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins of the ſunne, nuts, peares, apples, oliues, juncates, or banketing ſtuffe.</hi> And
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>De pane, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uis aliqui dubitarint; ſecurè tamen adhiberi poteſt ex conſuetudi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne.</hi> Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>as for bread, though ſome haue made queſtion of it, yet it may be taken without feare,</hi> and without danger. <hi>Bonacina</hi> ſaith,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis communiori vſu receptum ſit, vt in ſecunda refectione ij ſumantur cibi, quibus in die ieiunij veſcimur ante vel paſt prandium, vt ſunt vua, nuces, pon a, vel alia ex ſaccharo aut melle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecta; licitè tamen etiam ſumi poteſt iuſculum, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>odò ron ſit ex coctis cibis, qui tempore ieiunij interdicuntur. Poſſet etiam comedi piſciculus, aut exigua pars piſcis maioris.</hi> Martin. Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacina Sum. Moralis, to. 2. de Legib. Diſput. vlt. q. 1. punct. 3. num. 3. pag. 320.</note> 
                  <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be receiued by the more common cuſtome,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12743:16"/>that in the ſecond refection, thoſe meates may be taken, which on a faſting day we eate either before or after di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; ſuch as are raiſins, nuts, apples, or other things made of ſugar or honey: Yet broth alſo may lawfully be taken, ſo it be not of ſuch boyled meates, as are forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the time of the Faſt. A little fiſh alſo may be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, or a little portion of a greater fiſh.</hi> Theſe and ſuch like be the meates, which they allow men to feede on in the euening of their faſting day; and by ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of theſe in ſtead of their vſuall ſupper, they <hi>macerate</hi> the body mightily, and pull downe the pride of the fleſh, that it ſhall neuer dare to kicke againſt the ſpirit any more.</p>
               <p>Secondly, for the <hi>quantite</hi> of meate in their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening <hi>Collation,</hi> they ſay, it may be ſuch and ſo great, as the cuſtome of the place is. <hi>Fernandes</hi> ſaith, that the cuſtome of the Countrey is to bee obſerued. For,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Non eſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tale talem conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem ſeruare, licet quantitas ſit aliquantulu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis.</hi> Fernand. Exam. part. 2. §. 2. cap. 8. nu. 9. pa. 389.</note> 
                  <hi>it is no mortall ſinne to follow that, though the quantitie be ſomewhat great. Fumus</hi> ſaith,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Facientes Collationem groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam ſecundum conſuetudinem Rom. Curia vel tinelli, non fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt ieiunium.</hi> Aur. Armill. v. Ieiun. nu. 12. pag. 541.</note> that <hi>they which make a groſſe</hi> or great <hi>Collation, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the cuſtome of the Court of Rome, doe not violate their Faſt. Filliucius</hi> ſaith,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Etiamſi par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitas cibi, qui ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitur, non excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaret, adhuc ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men inducta con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuctudo liberat à culpa. — Non ergo adae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quata ratio liciti vſus Reſectiun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culae eſt, quia ſit exigua, ſed quia conſuetudo iam induxit.</hi> Filliuc. Moral. Qq. Tract. 27. part. 2. c. 2. nu. 26. pag. 279.</note> that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per or <hi>adequate reaſon for the lawfull vſe of the euen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Refection, is not becauſe it is little, but becauſe cuſtome hath brought it in:</hi> and that <hi>though the ſmall quantitie of meate ſhould not excuſe it, yet the receiued cuſtome doth free it from fault. Tolet</hi> ſaith, that
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>In Collatione verò eſt menſura: non debet enim eſse tanta, vt potius ſit Coena; tunc enim ſolueretur ieiuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. Quanta tamen debeat eſſe, conſideranda eſt conſuetudo communis patriae, quae viget com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muniter apud homines bonos &amp; timoratos. Non enim eſt peccatum mortale, talem conſuetudinem ſeruare, licet quantitas ſit aliquantulum grandis.</hi> Tolet Inſtruct. Sacer. l. 6. c. 2. nu. 6. pa. 738.</note> 
                  <hi>a meaſure</hi> is to be kept: <hi>for it may not bee ſo great, as that it doe rather become a Supper, then a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation;</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:12743:16"/>for <hi>then it were a breaking of a mans faſt. But</hi> to know <hi>how great it may be, reſpect is to be had to the common cuſtome of the country, vſed by men of tender conſcience. For it is no mortall ſinne, to obſerue that, though the quantitie bee ſomewhat great.</hi> Where we may obſerue by the way, that in this Ieſuites iudgement, men of <hi>tender conſciences</hi> among them, may vſe a great quantity of meat in their <hi>little Supper.</hi> But if ye deſire further to know what <hi>quantity</hi> men of <hi>tender conſcience</hi> in the Roman Church doe vſe, <hi>Azorius</hi> telleth vs,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>De Collatione noctis Natiuitatis Domini reſpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, — quòd conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo non ſolùm hominum parum de ſua ſalute ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituali curantiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Secularium; — Sed omnium Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricorum, imò Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligioſorum &amp; Praelatorum, etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Epiſcoporum &amp; Archiepiſcoporu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bonoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> invaluit, vt illa nocte opu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ientas Collationes fructuum et con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruarum — &amp; rerum ex ſaccha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro confectarum in ſuis menſis mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrentur: quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> menſis adfui, &amp; teſtis ſum, &amp; fic dico poſſe fieri illa nocte cum tali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, non ſeruata menſura ieiunij.</hi> Llamas Summ. Eclleſiaſt. part. 3. c. 5. §. 25. pa. 392, 393.</note> that <hi>in the Popes Court</hi> (and there I trow there be men of tender conſcience: ſure I am, their learned Doctors doe approue of the cuſtome there) that
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>In Curia Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana &amp; Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficia ſolet Refecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uncula ſumi pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo maior.</hi> Azor. Inſtit. part. 1. l. 7. c. 8. q. 8. pag. 557.</note> in <hi>the Popes Court they vſe to take a ſomewhat greater nights refection,</hi> then elſewhere is vſed. And therefore the common cuſtome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad cannot be excepted againſt, for being grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then men of <hi>tender conſciences</hi> doe approue. <hi>Llamas</hi> a Spaniſh Fryer and Doctor ſaith, that <hi>on Chriſtmas Eue it is the cuſtome not onely of Lay-men careleſſe of their ſaluation, but of all the Clergy, yea, of religious perſons and Prelates, yea, and of good Biſhops and Archbiſhops, to be ſerued at their tables with plentifull Collations of fruits, and conſerues, and confections of Sugar:</hi> that <hi>himſelfe hath beene at their tables, and is an eye wineſſe of it,</hi> and that <hi>it may at that time lawfully be done by ſuch men, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out obſeruing a meaſure of Faſting.</hi> And for the common cuſtome of other men, <hi>Beyerlinck</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of themſelues of the Roman Church, ſaith,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12743:17"/>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Nos longo et pleno prandio veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinam adijct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Refectiuncu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam, quae ſaepenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero in coenam degeneret.</hi> Bey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erlinck. Pro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt. Moral. in feſto Cinerum, text. 3. in fine, pag. 64.</note> 
                  <hi>We to a long and full dinner doe adde an euening re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, which oftentimes doth degenerate into a Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</hi> And this he mentioneth as a motherly indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth permit vnto her children. And <hi>Lindan</hi> ſaith, That ſuch hath beene the licenciouſneſſe of people, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the drinking of <hi>Wine</hi> and eating of <hi>Fiſh,</hi> things not vſed among the Ancients,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Immo &amp; canulam, — po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtremò etiam iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtam adderent Coenam, quae ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teribus procul dubio iuſtum fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſet prandium.</hi> Lindan. Pano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pl. l. 3. c. 11. pag. 89.</note> 
                  <hi>they added alſo</hi> Coenulam, <hi>a little Supper,</hi> and <hi>laſt of all,</hi> a <hi>full Supper, which the Ancients out of all queſtion would haue eſteemed a full dinner.</hi> Nor may any man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept againſt this laſt teſtimony, becauſe hee ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not of men of <hi>tender Conſciences,</hi> but of the ordinary multitude, who as he ſaith, had taken an irreligious liberty againſt the ſtrict Rules of their fore-fathers. For that limitation of <hi>Tolets,</hi> when he approueth only that cuſtome which is allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>tender conſciences,</hi> is but a flouriſh, or a varniſh to colour ouer their licencious dealing and doctrine with. For otherwiſe in deed and in truth, their Doctrine is, that in this caſe of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, cuſtome, whether it bee reaſonable or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, yet doth ſtill make the practice law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as I ſhall haue occaſion to ſhew more fully when I come to the laſt particular. And by this it may appeare, what <hi>quantity</hi> of meat is allowable in their little Supper, as they call it.</p>
               <p>In the third place now, wee are to conſider of the reaſon or ground of this Supper on Faſting-dayes; for it was not ſo from the beginning: and therefore it will be worth the labour to ſearch how it came in. But we neede not to beſtow any
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12743:17"/>great paines: themſelues doe tell vs, that
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quanquam olim ſumerentur [Collationes] tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum per modum medicinae ad cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandum ſomnum; iam tamen conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etudo obtinuit, vt etiam aliquid per modum nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tritionis ſumatur.</hi> Fernand. Exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. part. 2. c. 8. §. 2. nu. 9. pag. 389.</note> 
                  <hi>in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time,</hi> when it firſt beganne, <hi>it was allowed only by way of medicine to procure ſleepe,</hi> when men through abſtinence and emptineſſe could not take their naturall reſt: <hi>but that now cuſtome hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed, that it may bee vſed for nouriſhment</hi> or to feede the body. And (as another ſaith)
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Verius mihi videntur ſentire, qui eiuſmodi Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiunculam ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutè &amp; ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eſſelicitam ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brtrantur, tamet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi indigentiae ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſationem non habeat. Eam e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim à peccato de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendit &amp; liberat non ſomni velna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae neceſſitas, ſed co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuetudo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta: &amp; — fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teor quidem illa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> primò coepiſſe cauſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſomni capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endi, &amp; idcirco etiam indigentiae; more tamen &amp; conſuetudine eſt introductu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vt eâ abſolutè et ſimpliciter vtamur.</hi> Azor. Inſt part. 1. l. 7 c. 8. q. 4. p. 556.</note> 
                  <hi>at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning it was brought in to make men ſleepe, and ſo vpon a kinde of neceſsity: but now it is by cuſtome warranted, that we may vſe it without any ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect.</hi> And ſo, or to the ſame purpoſe ſpeake
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Fillinc. Moral. Qq. Tract. 27. part 2. c. 2. nu. 25. pag. 279. Leſſ de Iuſtit. &amp; Iure, l. 4. c. 2. Dubit. 2. §. Item ſumentes. pag. 719. Llamas Summ Eccleſ. part. 3. c. 5. §. 24. pag. 391, 392. Ioſeph. Angles in 4. de Iejun. q. 9. art. 2. diffic. 4. pag. 435.</note> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo. So in concluſion wee ſee, that beſides their <hi>ſet meale</hi> at noone-tide, they allow a little <hi>meale</hi> (as they call it) in the euening, conſiſting of <hi>bread, fruits, herbes, ſpices, confections,</hi> and a <hi>ſmall fiſh,</hi> and that in ſuch meaſure or <hi>quantity,</hi> be it ſmall or great, as by the cuſtome of the place is made vſuall; and all this for refreſhing and <hi>nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing</hi> of the body. And thus much they ſay.</p>
               <p>Now I ſay to the contrary, that this rule and cuſtome of theirs doth both ſwarue from all pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Antiquity, and doth croſſe the rules and properties of an holy Faſt, euen ſuch as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues doe require.</p>
               <p>Firſt, it is repugnant to <hi>Antiquity.
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Olim quum in diebus ieiuntoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad nonam coenaſſent omnes, nulla veſpertiná refectionculâ vtebantur: ſed poſtquam edere ſeu coenare coeperunt ad ſextam, qui iei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>um ſeruabant, introducla eſt refectiuncula veſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina.</hi> Azor inſtit. l. 7. c. 8. q 5. pag. 556.</note> For anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently</hi> (ſaith a Ieſuite) <hi>when all men faſted till three of the clocke, they vſed not any euening Refection: but
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12743:18"/>after that men on their faſting dayes beganne to eat their Supper at mid-day,</hi> (which was but a few yeeres agoe, and more then a thouſand yeeres after Chriſt) <hi>then was the euening Refection brought vp.</hi> And as another Ieſuite confeſſeth,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quia Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes teiunantibus cibum prohibent, potu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no prohibe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; ſubingreſſa ſunt, conniuentibus Hierarcbis, noſtrae nocturnae refecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unculae veteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus prorſus igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae, eo videlicet praetextu, ne po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus noceat.</hi> Piſa. de Abſtinent. ca. 14. pa. 167.</note> 
                  <hi>Becauſe the Canons of the Church doe forbid meat, but doe not forbid drinke: by the conniuence of the Prelates, our euening Refections vtterly vnknowne to the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents entred in, vpon pretence, for ſooth, leſt drinke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone ſhould doe hurt</hi> to the ſtomake. And <hi>Beyerlinck</hi> more freely &amp; plainly
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Illi vnicam vefectionem, ea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> tenuem ieiunan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus indulgeba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; nos longe et pleno prandio veſperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam adijcimus Refectiunculam, quae ſaepenumero in Coenam dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neret.</hi> Beyerl. Prompt. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. in feſto Cinerum, text. 3. pag. 63. 64.</note> 
                  <hi>They,</hi> ſaith he, (he meaneth the Ancients) <hi>permitted one only Refection, and that a ſpare one too: but we to a long and full dinner doe adde a ſmall Refection more, which oftentimes doth degenerate into a Supper.</hi> Thus themſelues con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe (as indeed they cannot with any face deny ſo cleare and euident a truth) that their <hi>euening Collation</hi> is a nouell cuſtome, vnheard of in the primitiue Church, or among good Chriſtians in the purer times.</p>
               <p>Secondly, this cuſtome of theirs in taking <hi>an euening Collation</hi> after a full noone-tide Dinner, doth croſſe and ouerthrow the nature and right vſe of a religious Faſt. For themſelues deſcribe a Faſt to conſiſt of <hi>one Refection onely;</hi> and they adde by way of reaſon, that if more were granted, it would take away the end aimed at in an holy Faſt, which is the afflicting of the body,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Probatur ex vniuerſali conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine, quae ſic in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretatae eſt praeceptum ieiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nij, vt non niſi femel in die com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edendum ſit. Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſter, Medina, Azorius, &amp; alij. Et iure merito<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> quia ſi pluries Refectio ſumeretur, non caſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garetur corpus; paſſim enim bomines contenti ſunt duplici refectione.</hi> Filliuc. Tract. 27. part. 2. c. 2. nu. 22. pag. 279. <hi>Quum homines communiter bis in die comedant, volens iciunare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet tantùm ſemel in die comedere. At<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ob id vnica comeſtio in die ieiunij (à media nocte in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam vſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> noſtem) eſt neceſſaria ad eſſentiam ieiunij. Ideo<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> bis parum comedens non cenſetar ieiunâſſe.</hi> Lorichius Theſaur. v. Ieiunium nu. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12743:18"/>men ordinarily are contented and ſatisfied with two Refections in a day; and conſequently, more then one, would be no affliction or chaſtiſement to the body.</hi> And they ſay true: and the truth of it is verified in this caſe. For who cannot without feeling any want of meat, goe to bed with ſuch a Collation in the euening, after he hath eaten a good dinner before? By their owne rules then it followeth, that the allowing of ſuch an <hi>euening Collation</hi> after a noone-tide dinner, is an aboliſhing of the right vſe of an holy Faſt.</p>
               <p>And thus much for their <hi>euening Refection</hi> or <hi>Collation:</hi> I come now to conſider their cuſtome of drinking on their faſting dayes, which I call a <hi>continuall Bever.</hi> For they doe allow a man in their Faſts to drinke what drinke he will, and as often as he will.
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>In Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtica Quadrage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſima vnica refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio tantum eſt conceſſa, &amp; in potatione nulla eſt appoſita limitatio.</hi> Io. Medina Cod. de Ieiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio. q. 2. in fine pag. 329.</note> In <hi>drinking in Lent faſts there is no limitation or reſtraint,</hi> how often it may bee vſed, ſaith <hi>Medina.</hi> And <hi>Fernandes,</hi> hauing firſt propounded the queſtion,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Poterítne quis in die ieiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nij ſaepius bibere, quamuis ſciat ſe potu maximè ali?</hi> Reſp. <hi>Pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> Fernand. Exam. p. 2. c. 8. nu. 17. pa. 392.</note> 
                  <hi>Whether vpon a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting day a man may drinke oftentimes, although hee doe know he ſhall be nouriſhed very much by it:</hi> hee anſwereth readily and roundly, <hi>Poterit, hee may doe it.</hi> And ſo <hi>Filliucius,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Dico potum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quae vel vini vel ceruiſiae, ſiue ante ſiue poſt prandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um; ſiue ſuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ad ſuſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tienem, ſiue non, haud frangere ieiunium.</note> I ſay</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>that drinking of water, or wine, or beere, whether it be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or after dinner; whether it be taken for nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men or not, doth no way breake a mans faſt.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeably hereunto the reſt of their Doctors doe teach, as I ſhewed before out of <hi>AZorius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now lay theſe things together, that vpon a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting day a man may eat a full dinner, and after that in the euening take a <hi>little Supper,</hi> which by
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12743:19"/>vertue of common cuſtome doth grow to a true or iuſt meale many times; and beſides all this,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Colligitur, quòd non prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tur bibere quantum quis voluerit ante &amp; poſt comeſtionem. Sequitur praete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaeum non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringere te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſumit Collati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem: nam am plius quàm ſen el in die non come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.</hi> Barthol. Medina In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct. Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſariorum, l. 1. c. 14 §. 10. pag. 142. <hi>Nondici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Refectio, ſed Refectiuncula.</hi> Bonacina Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. Theol. to. 2. diſp. vlt. q. 1. punct. 3. pag. 320.</note> may drinke <hi>ſweete wines</hi> and <hi>ſtrong drinkes,</hi> what he will, at all times of the day, and then tell me, what great penance is to be found in a Popiſh Faſt? They ſay, that drinking of the <hi>beſt wines,</hi> is no feeding; and that eating a <hi>Collation</hi> in the euening, and <hi>ſpices</hi> and <hi>conſerues</hi> at other times of the day, is no <hi>Refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi> But <hi>Ionathan,</hi> when he <hi>taſted a little honey vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the point of his ſpeare,</hi> felt himſelf much refreſhed by it; as it is 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.27, 28, 29. And we finde it in experience, that ſtrong drinkes, ſpicerie and confections, doe ſo ſatisfie the deſire of nature, that they take away a mans appetite from his meate; and themſelues confeſſe, that <hi>wines,</hi> and ſtrong <hi>drinkes,</hi> and <hi>Electuaries,</hi> doe nouriſh the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and breede blood and ſpirits. What gluttons then are they in their religious Faſts, that eſteeme all this as no <hi>refection</hi> of the body? And if it bee a
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Voco Refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem, ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem cibi ad alendum corpus,</hi> Filliuc. Tract. 27. part. 2. cap. 2 nu. 22. pag. 279 <hi>&amp; Sumere ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculum ſi roti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ad ſuſtentationem naturae, eſt procul dubio iterum comedere.</hi> Caiet. Summula, v. Ieiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium. fol. 120. pag. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Refection,</hi> (as they which vſe it doe feele, and all that conſider it, euen themſelues not excepted, will confeſſe it;) then a Popiſh Faſt is not contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the definition of a true Faſt, one eſſentiall part whereof is this, that there be taken <hi>one onely Refection</hi> for the ſpace of a whole day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:12743:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII. </hi>The Time of refection in a Popiſh Faſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hus I haue done with the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond particular, concerning their <hi>Indulgence,</hi> namely, the <hi>Number</hi> of their Refections: the third is, the <hi>time</hi> that they preſcribe or allow for the breaking of their Faſt. For in the ordinary Faſts of the Church, one <hi>refection</hi> in the day hath euer beene allowed, but that in times paſt, when Religion was not defaced with ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition and hypocriſie, was towards the end of the day; that ſo nature might bee chaſtened, and yet not deſtroyed. But in the Faſts of the Church of Rome, this vſage of the Ancients is peruerted alſo. For clearing of which point, I will ſet down their owne ſayings and concluſions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They ſay in the generall, that that time for breaking of a mans Faſt is lawfull, which cuſtome doth approue. So <hi>Medina</hi> ſaith,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hic taman non eſt immor en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, nec opus eſt ſcrupulos inferre. Seruetur in hoc, ſicut in alijs mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis patria conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etudo,</hi> Ioh. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina Cod. de ieiun. q. 6. pag. 338. Col. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>that concerning this point we are not to make any ſtop, nor is it needfull to moue any ſcruples: but let the cuſtome of the Country be obſerued herein, as in many other things. Fernan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> firſt propoundeth the queſtion:
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Interr. Quae eſt hora co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>petens ſumendi cibum?</hi> Reſp. <hi>Ea, quae ſecundum conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etudinem loci ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uari ſolet paulò plus minuſue.</hi> Fernand. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am. part. 2. c. 8. §. 2. nu. 4. pag. 388.</note> 
                  <hi>What is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent houre for receiuing of meate</hi> on a faſting day? and then he ſhapeth the anſwer to it, <hi>That houre which is vſed to be kept according to the cuſtome of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:12743:20"/>place; or thereabouts not much vnder or ouer.</hi> And <hi>Cajetan,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Hora quidem conueniens, ante quam non eſt comedendum, eſt meridies groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sâ aeſtimatione. Sed vbi commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niter non ſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur à ieiunanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, poteſt quis comedere illâ ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>râ, quâ co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ieiunantes ibi comedunt.</hi> Caie. Summul. v. Ieiun. fol. 120. pag. 1.</note> The conuenient houre</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>before which we muſt not eate, is mid-day: But where that is not commonly obſerued, a man may eate at that houre, at which thoſe that doe faſt, doe commonly eate in that place.</hi> And to the ſame purpoſe ſpeake o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo.</p>
               <p>Secondly, for more particular determination of the time, they ſay, that the cuſtome among them is, to dine on their faſting daies about mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, or an houre or two ſooner. <hi>Cajetan</hi> ſaith, that
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Nunc autem Religioſi, etiam multum ante me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridiem aeſtiuo tempore &amp; in Quadrageſima videntur come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere.</hi> Caietan. Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>euen their religious men, in ſummer and in Lent doe eate their meale long before mid-day.</hi> And <hi>Azorius</hi> telleth vs, that their
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Seculares reiunium laxant ac ſoluant, hyeme quidem vnâ ante meridiem horâ; aeſtate verò dua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus fere horis an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re meridiem: Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nachi verò &amp; caeteri religioſi, hyeme aut ſemi horâ ante meridiem, aut in meridie, aut etiam horâ ante meridiem; aeſtate verò vnâ horâ integrâ, aut etiam vnâ &amp; ſemi borâ ante meridiem.</hi> Azor. Inſtit part. 1. l. 7. c. 11. pag. 564. Col. 1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Seculars doe breake off their Faſt in winter, one houre before mid-day, and in ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer almoſt two houres:</hi> and that <hi>Monckes and other religious perſons doe it, in winter, about mid-day, or halfe an houre, or a whole houre before; and in ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, a whole houre, or an houre &amp; an halfe before mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day.</hi> And to him agree
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Filliuc. Tract. 27. part. 2. c. 4. nu 73. pa. 284.</note> 
                  <hi>Filliucius,</hi> and
<note n="(e)" place="margin">Reginald, Prax. l. 4. nu. 156. pag. 152.</note> 
                  <hi>Reginaldus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, They thinke it not vnlawfull, to breake Faſt longer before noonetide, if ſo it be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. <hi>Barthol. Medina</hi> ſaith,
<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                     <hi>De hoc non eſt ſcrupulus habendus. Nam videtur mos eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeinter Chriſtianos introductus, quòd edere ſufficit quaſi borâ ante meridiem; ſuntque nonnulli Doctores ſentientes ſeruari ieiunium, ſi manè comeditur tribus aut quatuor anticipatis horis ante aneridicm, modò non comedatur niagis quàm ſemel.</hi> Barthol. Medina Inſtruct. Confeſ. l. 1. c. 14. §. 10. pag. 143.</note> that <hi>wee are not to ſtand ſcrupulouſly vpon this point, becauſe the cuſtome is brought in among Chriſtians, that it ſufficeth to eate about an houre before noone: and that ſome Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12743:20"/>think that a Faſt is kept, if men eate in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, three or foure houres before mid-day, ſo they eate not oftener then once.</hi> And he and they ſpeake according to their owne grounds and principles. For ſeeing cuſtome is of ſuch power with them, both in this and in other things, that it may diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>null and cancell the Churches orders in greater matters then this is, as
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Reginald. l. 4. nu. 156. pa. 152.</note> 
                  <hi>Reginaldus</hi> ſaith it may; then if cuſtome haue preuailed to haue Dinner many houres before noone, it will be ſafe inough to vſe it.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, becauſe the rules and Canons of the Church did require, that their after-noone ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, which they call <hi>Officium Nonae,</hi> their <hi>noone or ninth-houre Seruice,</hi> which was at three of the Clocke after mid-day, ſhould bee ſaid in their Churches, before they did breake off their Faſt; they tranſlated their after-noone Seruice to the fore-noone, that ſo they might eate their Supper about mid-day, or ſooner. And though they altered the time, in this manner, from the ninth houre to the ſixt, or ſooner, that is, from three of the Clocke to twelue; yet they kept the old name of their Seruice ſtill, and called it <hi>Preces Nonae, the noone or ninth-houre Prayers.</hi> And from hence a learned man of their own Church obſerueth, that
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſt hoc no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris moribus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptum in officio Eccleſiaſtico, vt diebus ieiuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum Preces No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae, &amp; quas horâ nonâ dicere opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebat, ante pran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium recitentur. Et vulgus Ruſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum apud Walones meridiem vocant Nonam, &amp; Flandri tàm Ruſtici quàm Ciues meridiem ſuo idiomate vocant Nonam; &amp; ad pulſum duodecimae, quae eſt nobis hora meridiei, obtinuit vetus proborum Catholicorum conſuetudo, vt detecto capite oretur Deus &amp; cogitetur mors Chriſti, quae accidit hord nonâ</hi> Antiq. Liturg. to. 1. feriâ 4 quatuor Temporum cap. 1. pa. 100.</note> 
                  <hi>in Flanders, and among the Wallons, mid-day or twelue of the Clocke hath beene vſed to bee called Noone.</hi> And ſo wee ſee it is called among vs heere
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:12743:21"/>in England. Nor did they reſt contented with this; but becauſe the
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tempore Quadrageſima non manducant ieiunantes ante dictas veſperas: ſed dicunt illas omnes Eccleſiae decimâ horâ, vt vndecimâ come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant.</hi> Hieron. Llamas Summ. Eccleſ. part. 3. c. 5. § 26. pa. 394. <hi>Erat illa conſuetudo in Quadrageſima, vt horá nonâ, hoc eſt, noſtro more, horâ tertiâ poſt meridiem, incipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent fieri miſsae, &amp; poſt miſſas O<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fficium Veſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinum, ac deinde ſolueretur ieiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Cui legi noſtri mores fraudem faciunt. Ita e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim dicimus miſſas vt vnà cum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſpertinali Officio, quod illis in Quadrageſima continuò rectè ſubiungimus, finiantur hora ſexta, quae reſpondet noſtrae due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decimae ſeu meridiei, &amp; tunc ſoluimus ietunium.</hi> Antiq. Liturg. to. 2. feriâ ſextâ poſt Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neres. pag. 105.</note> Canons required, that in Lent time they ſhould faſt till after the <hi>Veſpers</hi> or Euening Seruice was ended, which was toward night; they ſaid their <hi>Veſpers</hi> or Euening Seruice in the morning, that hauing diſpatched them, they might goe to meat at 11. or 10. of the clocke. And ſo
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quum ieiunium, quod antea non niſi ad nonam horam, ſiue ad tert am nobis po eridianam ſoluebatur, ante meridiem interrumperetur, atque eam in rem non modò myſteria, ſed &amp; veſperae ſuum mentientes tempus anticiparentur; factum eſt vt—horae ieiuniorum labore moleſtiores praeciderentur.</hi> Lindan. Panopl. lib. 3. cap. 11. pag. 89.</note> 
                  <hi>their Euening Seruice</hi> (as a learned Biſhop of their owne doth obſerue) <hi>belyeth his time,</hi> being performed long before that time of the day. And the reaſon of all this was, becauſe (as
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tunc veſpertinae borae poſt horam tertiam poſt meridiem celebrabantur; quam horam quum multis eſſet difficile expe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tare vt coenam ſumerent; poſtea vſu mductum eſt, vt ante vel iuxta meridiem celebrarentur, vt illis finitis, competens ad co edendum tempus fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus relinqueretur.</hi> Io. Medina Cod. de Ieiun. q. 6 pag. 338. Col. 2.</note> themſelues doe tell vs) <hi>it was too long for many to ſtay till three of the clocke for their ſupper; and therefore it was brought in by cuſtome, that the Euening Seruice ſhould be ſaid before or about mid-day, that that being ended, there might be left a competent houre, for Gods faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full people to eate</hi> on their faſting day. The ſumme is, they made haſte with their Seruice, that they might not ſtay long for their Dinner.</p>
               <p>Now againſt this part of their <hi>Indulgence,</hi> I ſay,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That it is againſt all practice of Antiquitie in Scriptures. For, the cuſtome related there, was to abſtaine till Euening, or the Sunne-ſetting; as may appeare by the examples of Faſts recorded in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12743:21"/>Scriptures, and gathered and alledged by <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> to that purpoſe.
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>In Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento veteri quum de ieiuniis agitar, borae ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spertinae fit men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, Jud.</hi> 20. <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunauerunt illa die vſque ad ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperam. Idem ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur.</hi> 2 Reg. 1. &amp; 3. <hi>&amp; alibi. Ex quo intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus apud Patres Veteris Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti ieiunium fuiſse ſemel tantùm, idque ad vesperam eibum capere.</hi> Bellar. de bo. oper. in partic. l. 2. c. 2. §. unam igitur.</note> 
                  <hi>In the Old Teſtament,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>where there is ſpeech of faſting, there is mention made of the euentide,</hi> as the time when they broke off their Faſt: as <hi>Iudg.</hi> 20.26. <hi>They faſted that day vntill euen.</hi> And <hi>the like is ſaid,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.12. <hi>They mourned and wept and faſted vntill euen for Saul and for Ionathan,</hi> and 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.35. <hi>So doe God to me, and more alſo, if I taſte bread or ought elſe, till the ſunne be downe. And ſo elſe where. Whereby we vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>that among the Fathers of the Old Teſtament, a Faſt was, to eate meate but once on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and that in the euening.</hi> The caſe is both cleare and confeſſed; and therefore needeth no further proofe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I ſay, that it is againſt the practice of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Chriſtian Church. For
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>In principio n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſientis Eccleſiae ieiunium vſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad ſolis occaſum ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debatur. Et ratio eſt, quia Apoſtoli formam ieiunandi accepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt ab antiquis Patribus, quibus praeceptum erat, vſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad veſperam ieiunium ſeruare: &amp; ita Diſcipuli Apoſtolorum per multa tempora ſeruaue ut.</hi> Lege Euſeb. l. 2. Hiſt. Eccl. c. 17. &amp; Baſil. Serm. 1. de Ieiun. &amp; D. Ambroſ. Serm. 33 &amp; B. Aug. Ep. 86. Ioſeph. Angles in 4. Sent part. 1. de Iej. q. 9. ar. 3. Diff. 1. pa. 440. v. Antiq. Liturg. to, 2 feriâ 6. poſt Cineres. p. 104.</note> 
                  <hi>in the beginning of the Church, Faſts were continued till the Sunne-ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ioſeph Angles.</hi> He addeth, that the <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thereof was, becauſe the Apoſtles receiued their forme of faſting from the Fathers of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who were commanded to keepe their Faſt till e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening. And ſo the Apoſtles Scholers kept it for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeeres after.</hi> And for proofe thereof, hee bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs <hi>reade Euſebius, Baſil, Ambroſe,</hi> and <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine.</hi> And if he had pleaſed, he might haue added others moe. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> citeth <hi>Tertullian, Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius, Baſil, Epiphan. Ambroſe, Hierom, Prudenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Paulinus, Chryſoſtome, Auguſtine, Caſsian, Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, Gregorie, Bernard, Micrologus, Gratian.</hi> Out
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12743:22"/>of which Authors he concludeth, that
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chriſtiani Veteres ieiunia non ſoluebant, niſi horâ nonâ ab ortuſolis, vel etiam horâ ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſportmâ in Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drageſima. — St. Auguſt. in Epiſt.</hi> 86. <hi>ad Caſula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, paſſim acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit non prandere pro co quod eſt ieiunare, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra non ieiunare, pro eo quod eſt pran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere. — apud Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teres — inaudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt prorſus, vt ante horam no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, quae eſt ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia poſt meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em, ieiunium quodcunque ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatur: quemad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum etiam nulla eſt apud Veteres mentio binae Refectionis, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de ieiunijs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur.</hi> Bellar. de bonis operi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus in part. l. 2. cap. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>The Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents did not breake off their Faſts til three of the clock in the afternoone, or till euening in Lent time: that in S. Auguſtines dialect, Not to faſt, and to dine; or to faſt, and not to dine, is all one:</hi> and <hi>that it is a thing neuer heard of among the Ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, that any Faſt ſhould be broke off before three of the clock in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone.</hi> And (as another learned man noteth)
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tanta fuit alim cura non comedendi ante nonam tempore ieiunij, vt pran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dêre &amp; non ieiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare paſſim om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus Veterum libris ſint ſyno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyma.</hi> Antiq. Liturg. to. 1. feria quarta, 4. temporum. cap. 1. pag. 99.</note> 
                  <hi>So great was the care in old time, not to eate before three of the clocke on their faſting daies, that to dine, and not to faſt, are euerywhere in all the Bookes of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, words of the ſame ſignification.</hi> And the like is acknowledged generally by the reſt of their lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men: as indeed the caſe is ſo cleare, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denied, or any way ſhifted off. And heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we may reſt ſatisfied for this point: Onely I will adde one conſideration more, that the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, though they did eate but one onely meale, and that a ſparing one; yet they eſteemed it not the keeping of a faſting day, if they tooke that meale about noonetide or dinner time. And hence it was, that becauſe the Church did forbid any faſting daies to be kept between Eaſter and Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunday, that they might expreſſe their ioy for Chriſts Reſurrection; the ancient Monkes, not willing to vſe any fuller diet then they were accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed vnto at other times, did only change their <hi>ſupper</hi> into a <hi>dinner,</hi> without altering the <hi>quantitie</hi> of their meate. So St. <hi>Hierome,</hi> relating the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes of the Coenobitae, that is, ſuch-religious perſons as liued together in a Collegiate life, ſaith
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12743:22"/>among other things,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>A Paſcha ad Pentecoſten Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae mutantur in Prandia; quò &amp; traditioni Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticae ſatisfiat, &amp; ventrem cibe non onerent du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate.</hi> Hieron. Epiſt. 22. ad Euſt. pa. 186. F.</note> 
                  <hi>From Eaſter to Pentecoſt, their Suppers are changed into Dinners, that ſo they may both ſatisfie the Orders of the Church, and yet not ſtuffe the belly with a double portion of meate.</hi> And in <hi>Caſsian</hi> we finde, that one hauing moued a doubt, how a religious man, accuſtomed to faſting and ſpare diet, might paſſe this long time of Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie betweene Eaſter and Whitſuntide, without making the fleſh too wanton, if hee ſhould feede more fully or finely then before; anſwere was made, to this purpoſe; that
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vt ergo &amp; diebus feſtiuis ſtatutae conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ſolennitatis conſernetur, &amp; ſaluberrimus par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimoniae modus minimè tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datur; ſufficit vt indulgentiam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionis eò vſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> progredi patia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, vt cibus, qui horâ diei n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nâ fuerat capiendus, paulò citiùs, id eſt, ſextà horâ pro feſtiuitatis tempore capiatur, ea ratione dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxat, vt eſcarum ſolitus modus vel qualitas non mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetur.</hi> Caſſian. Collat. 21. cap. 23. pag. 1030.</note> 
                  <hi>for the keeping of this feſtiuall ſolemnitie appointed by the Church, without breaking of the wholſome order of their ſpare diet; it would ſuffice ſo farre onely to remit of their rigour, that the meate which was vſed to be taken at three of the clocke in the afternoone, ſhould for that ſpace of time be taken ſomewhat ſooner, that is, about twelue of the clocke, in that maner onely, that neither the wented meaſure, nor the qualitie of their meate bee changed.</hi> By which places it is apparent, that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie thought a mans Faſt to be broken, if there were nothing elſe in it, but onely this, that he did eate about mid-day; though the <hi>quantitie</hi> and <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie</hi> of his meate were altogether the ſame that is vſuall on faſting daies. And this may ſerue to ſhew how vnlike the Church of Rome is in this point alſo, to all Antiquitie both of the Iewiſh and Chriſtian Church.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, I ſay, it is againſt the nature of a Faſt, as it is deſcribed by Popiſh Doctors. For, a Faſt is for afflicting of the body by ſubtraction of food. And therefore, (as <hi>Thomas</hi> ſpeaking of this
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:12743:23"/>very point, ſaith,)
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vnde aportet, quòd aliquid ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat ſupra com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munem conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem; ita ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men quòd per hoc non multùm na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura grauetur. Eſt autem debita &amp; communis conſuetudo come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendi hominibus circa horam ſex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam; tum quia iam videtur eſſe completa digeſtio nocturno tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, naturali calo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re interiùs reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cato propter fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus noctis cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtans; &amp; dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſio humoris per membra, coöper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ante ad hoc calo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re diei, vſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum ſolis aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum: tum etiam, quia tunc praeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puè natura corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris humani indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get iuvari contra exteriorem aeris calorem, ne hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mores interiùs adurantur. Et idea vt ieiunans aliquam affictio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſentiat pro culpae ſatisfactio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, conueniens hora comedendi taxaturieiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantibus circa horam nonem.</hi> Aquin. 2.2. q. 147. art. 7. in C.</note> 
                  <hi>Something muſt be added, aboue the common cuſtome; yet ſo, that nature hereby be not burdened ouermuch. But the cuſtome of eating about mid-day, is the due and common time; both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe now digeſtion ſeemeth to be fully ended in the night ſeaſon, naturall heate being called inward, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the externall cold about, and the diffuſion of the moiſture or iuice by the members of the body ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth now alſo compleate, the heate of the day coopera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thereunto, vntill the higheſt aſcent of the Sunne. And alſo becauſe mans nature doth eſpecially then ſtand in need to be relieued againſt the externall heate of the ayre, leſt the humours within bee burned by it. And therefore that he that fasteth may feele ſome af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, a conuenient houre of eating is impoſed about three of the clocke.</hi> And <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and <hi>Valentia,</hi> and <hi>Piſanus,</hi> beſides other moe, in their <hi>definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of a Faſt, or among the <hi>eſſentiall</hi> things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to it, doe (as I ſhewed in the beginning) require this for one, that in a Faſt, the <hi>abſtinence is to be longer then at other times,</hi> and the refection is to be <hi>later and after the vſuall time of</hi> Dinner, that by this forbearance of meate, nature may feele a want of food, and the body may be affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by it. But the vſuall time of feeding on ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie dayes, is about noone, or eleuen of the clocke, or not before tenne at the ſooneſt. And therefore when the Church of Rome doth allow mento eate their dinner on faſting dayes at thoſe houres or ſooner; it doth by this indulgence o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow the <hi>eſſence</hi> of a Faſt.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:12743:23"/>
               <p>To this <hi>Bellarmine</hi> anſwers,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quando Veteres definie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt horam no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam pro ſolutione ieiunij, tempus ordinarium ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum ſumendi ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebat eſſe meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. Satis enim eſſe putauerunt ad carnis afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem &amp; caſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem, ſi ad ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium trium bora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, id eſt, ab bora ſexta, vſque ad nonam refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur. Noſtro verò tempore magna pars ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum non horâ ſextâ, ſed tertiá prandere ſolet. Ex quo ſequitur, vt ſi tempore ieiunij cibum ſumant horâ ſextâ, hoe eſt, ad meridiem, tribus horis ſeriùs ad reficiendum corpus accedant, quàm ordinariè ſoleant; ac per hoc ab antiqua conſuetudine non recedant.</hi> Bellar. de bo. oper. in part. l. 2. c. 2. §. Addimus.</note> 
                  <hi>that when the Ancients did preſcribe three of the clocke for the breaking of a mans Faſt, men then did vſe to dine about mid day. For they thought that this was ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t affliction for the fleſh, if the refection of the body were deferred for three houres ſpace, namely, from twelue, till three of the clocke in the afternoone. But now-a-dayes,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the greateſt part of men is accuſtomed to dine, not at twelue, but at nine of the clocke in the morning. Whence it followeth, that if men do now in the time of their faſt, dine about noone-tide, they come to feed the body three houres later then ordinary: and ſo they keepe the old cuſtome ſtill.</hi> Thus the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. But <hi>Filliucius</hi> ſaith,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vt omittam communiter ieiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandi difficultatem ſentiri in Refectiuncula Veſpertina, non autem in prorogatione prandij, quae vix differre ſolet ab hora conſueta prande<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di in diebus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munibus.</hi> Fil. tract. 27. p. 2. c. 4. nu. 71. p. 284.</note> 
                  <hi>that commonly the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie or hardneſſe which is in faſting, is felt in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening refection, and not in the forbearing of dinner, which doth ſcarce differ from the ordinary houre of dinner on other dayes.</hi> Which anſweres of theirs doe indeed deſerue no reply, becauſe they are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently friuolous. For where doe men now-a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies ordinarily dine at nine of the clocke, as <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> ſaith? Or if they doe ſo in ſome places, yet certainely in moſt places it is not ſo; and what will he ſay for the Faſts that be there vſed? Or if it were ſo in moſt Countries, yet they doe allow men to dine on their faſting dayes, at eleuen or tenne of the clocke, or ſooner. And then what great penance were there in that forbearance, lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then which euery man muſt and will yeeld vnto at their greateſt Feaſts, before the Cookes
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12743:24"/>can be ready? And for their little refection at night, that ſure pincheth the body but eaſily, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch as before was declared, and after a full meale at noone-tide before. Theſe friuolous an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers then deſerue no ſerious reply; nor would I feare leſt any man ſhould be perſwaded or miſ-led by them: yet I thought it not amiſſe to relate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that men might ſee both what poore and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſhifts they are driuen to, for defence of their looſe and licencious Faſts: and alſo how in things euident to the eye, the one doth croſſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict the other; <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaying that the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomarie houre of dinner is now-a-daies about nine of the clocke; and <hi>Filliucius</hi> affirming, that there is ſmall difference betweene their dinner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houre on their faſting day, and on another day. But a deſperate cauſe requireth ſuch miſerable ſhifts.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, I ſay, that this dining at noone vpon faſting dayes, ſprang from indeuorion &amp; want of zeale, or from Epicuriſme, &amp; a loue of the belly. I preſume in reaſon I may well thinke ſo, ſeeing no other probable cauſe can bee imagined, why it ſhould otherwiſe be admitted and receiued. But I ſhall not neede to ſtand vpon coniectures or ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, how probable ſoeuer otherwiſe they bee. For themſelues doe acknowledge as much as I ſay. <hi>Filliucius</hi> ſaith,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Oline apud Hebraeos ieiunia produce bantur vſque ad occaſum ſolis &amp; apud Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teres Chriſtianos idem erat in more poſitum.— Qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis deinde, fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uore intepeſcente; coeperit etiam quoad horam temitti.</hi> Filliue. Tract. 27 part. 2. c. 4. nu. 64. pag. 28<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that <hi>in old time, the Iewes fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted till ſunne-ſeting, and that the ſame was the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the ancient Chriſtians alſo; although after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, zeale waxing cold, they began to abate of the houre.</hi> And to the ſame purpoſe ſpeaketh <hi>Azori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:12743:24"/>For hauing firſt ſaid, that the Hebrews did vſe to faſt till night; and that thence the old Chriſtians were accuſtomed to keepe the ſame order, he addeth;
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Deinde te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſcente ſenſim vetere illo ferue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, coeptum eſt ſolui ieiunium primò quidem antequam ſol oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cideret, deinde verò etiam pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis horis ante ſolis abſceſſum. Nam coena ſumi coepit ad horam nonam, hoc eſt, tribus horis poſt meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em exactis, &amp; totidem ante ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem occidentem.</hi> Azor. Inſtit. part. 1. l. 7. c. 11. q 1. pag. 563, 564.</note> 
                  <hi>Afterward, the old zeale wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cold by degrees, the Faſt began firſt to be broke off before the Sunne went downe; and after that, a few houres before ſunne-ſetting. For they began to eate their ſupper at three of the clocke, that is, three houres after mid-day, and as many houres before the ſunne ſet.</hi> And if zeale may be ſaid then to waxe cold, when they preuented the old time, by taking their ſupper at 3. of the clocke in the afternoone, then we may boldly ſay, that now zeale is <hi>key-cold,</hi> or quite <hi>quenched</hi> in the Church of Rome, ſeeing ſhe alloweth her children on their faſting dayes, to eate their dinner before the mid-day. And ſo, or more ſharpely then ſo, doth <hi>Fileſacus</hi> cenſure this diſorder;
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Noſtrâ im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becillitate irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giosâ (vt ita di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam) factum eſt, vt ad meridiem cibum ſumamus, ſoluamuſque ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunium.</hi> Fileſac. de Quadrag. cap. 6. pag. 437.</note> 
                  <hi>It is come to paſſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>by our ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious infirmitie, that we take meate at mid-day, and ſo breake off the Faſt.</hi> He meaneth, that men did pretend <hi>infirmitie,</hi> becauſe it was too long for their feeble bodies to forbeare meat, as the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents did; but that the true reaſon was not weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and indiſpoſition of body, but irreligion and deadneſſe of ſoule. And this may ſuffice to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the time of their eating on faſting dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:12743:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V. </hi>The Quantity of meat and drink in a Popiſh Faſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He fourth particular is the <hi>quantity</hi> of meat and drink allowable in the Church of Rome in their holy Faſts. And for that, I find no <hi>ſtint</hi> among them, but that euery man meaſure himſelfe by the belly. But that their meaning may more plainely and diſtinctly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, I will firſt conſider the <hi>quantity</hi> that they allow in their dinner, and then in their drinkings.</p>
               <p>And firſt, for their <hi>dinner</hi> on faſting dayes, they ſay, That he
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Excedeus in quantitate cibi, vtcunque rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens ab aequalita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te quantitat is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminatae, non frangit ieiunium.</hi> Ioſ. Angles in 4. de Ieiun. q. 9. dub. 5. Concl. 2. pag. 432.</note> 
                  <hi>who exceedeth in the quantity of meat, how much ſoeuer he ſwarue from the equality or euen meaſure of the ſet quantity, breaketh not his faſt.</hi> They ſay,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sequitur, quòd ſi quis in die ieiunij illa tria ex intente ſeruet, &amp; tamen in vnica refecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one quam ſumit, regulam tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantiae per gulam excedat, ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciat praecepto de ieiunando, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doquidem ſub illo praecepto non ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit quantitas re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionis.</hi> Ioh. Medina. Cod. de Ieiun. q. 11. pag. 354.</note> 
                  <hi>that if a man doe with intent and purpoſe keepe the three things which they require in a Faſt, and yet in that one refection or dinner which hee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, doe through gluttony exceede the rule of tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; yet he doth ſatisfie or ſufficiently keepe the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of faſting; becauſe the quantitie of the dinner doth not fall vnder that precept, or is not compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in it.</hi> Againe they ſay,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque quis ſemel tantum in die horâ praeſcriptâ comederit, &amp; à cibis vetitis abſtinuerit; quicquid aliud comedat vel bibat, ſiue moderatè ſiue immoderatè, &amp; ſiue delectabiliter, ſiue aliter, nonfrangit ieinnium Eccleſiaſticum.</hi> Reginald. lib. 4. nu. 163 pag. 154.</note> 
                  <hi>Whenſoeuer a man doth eate but once in the day, at the appointed houre, and abſtaineth from forbidden meates; whatſoeuer elſe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12743:25"/>he either eateth or drinketh, whether moderately or immoderately, and whether to delight appetite or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, he breaketh not the Faſt of the Church.</hi> Yea,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Interrog. Quantum licet comedere die ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunij?</hi> Reſp. <hi>Quantum quis edere poterit, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quendo de ratione praecepti.</hi> Fern. Exam. part. 2. c. 8. §. 2. pag. 389.</note> but is there no meaſure how much a man may eate? Yes. <hi>He may eate as much as he can, for ought that the Precept of the Church doth require.</hi> Yea, but ſay that a man doe gormandize, how then?
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Qui vſque ad ingurgitatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem comederet, talis exceſſus il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitus eſſet, ſed non ex hoc ſolui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ieiunium.</hi> Iac. de Graff. deciſion. aur. part. 2. l. 2. c. 16. nu. 22. pa. 158.</note> 
                  <hi>If a man ſhould eate till he glut himſelfe, that exceſſe were vnlawfull, but heereby his Faſt is not broken.</hi> Well: but
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sed an hi ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent praecepta ieiunij, qui ſemel comedendo tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cibi ſumunt, tot cibarijs &amp; condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis vtuntur adingluuiem vſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que, vt nullam carnis afflictione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſentiant, immò gulam impenſiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè irritent, libi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem excitent tantum cibi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes vnico prandiò quantum ſit tribus hominibus ſatis ad congruam eorum ſuſtentationem?</hi> Reſp. <hi>Quòd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>onſideratis conſiderandis, haec quaeſtio poteſt ita decidi, quòd ſi nos loquimur quoad ſubſtantiam praecepti, ieiunium non diſsoluitur, &amp; ita poteſt habere locum communis opinie, ſcilicet hoſee ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines ieiunij precepto ſatisfeciſſe. — Aut verò loquimur de ieiunio quoad meritum, &amp; ita nonſatisfaciunt.</hi> Iacob. Graff. part. 1. l. 2. c. 37. nu. 39. pag. 217.</note> what if a man at his <hi>meale take ſo much meate, vſe ſo many diſhes and ſawces, euen to gluttony and gormandizing, that he feeleth no affliction of the fleſh, yea that he doth exceedingly prouoke his glutton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous appetite, ſtirre vp luſt, and take ſo much meate at one dinner, as may be ſufficient for three men to feede vpon in a conuenient ſort;</hi> doth this man keepe the Lawes of faſting? <hi>I anſwer</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iacobus de Graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fijs) that if we ſpeake according to the ſubſtance of the Precept, his Faſt is not broken: and in this ſenſe the common opinion may be admitted, which is, that theſe men doe ſatisfie the Precept of the Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning faſting. Or elſe we may ſpeake of Faſting, with reſpect to the merit of it; and ſo theſe men doe not ſatisfie or fulfill the Precept.</hi> Thus theſe men ſpeake for the <hi>quantitie</hi> of their meate at dinner. And their practice is not vnlike their doctrine. For,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Nos prandia ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mimus, eaque talia, vt praeteritam abſtinentiam copiâ &amp; varietate ciborum facilè compenſemus.</hi> Beyerl. prompt. in feſto Cinerum, tex. 3. pag. 63.</note> 
                  <hi>We</hi> (ſaith <hi>Beyerlinck</hi>) <hi>take our dinners</hi> on our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12743:26"/>dayes, <hi>and they ſuch, that we may eaſily by the ſtore and varietie of meates, make amends for the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence that is paſt.</hi> But <hi>Lindan</hi> ſpeaketh more broad, and ſaith that <hi>the faſts of their Catholikes are euery where ſuch Faſts as Epicures doe keepe.</hi> To which purpoſe I haue cited his words
<note n="*" place="margin">Treatiſe of Faſting. cap. 4.</note> elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</p>
               <p>The like they ſay for the <hi>quantitie</hi> or meaſure of their <hi>drinking</hi> all times of the day. For,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bene poteſt bibere ante pran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium &amp; poſt prandium, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum videbitur illi abſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> peccato non ieiunandi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Verum eſt, quòd peccabit peccalo gulae, &amp;c.</hi> Rod. Summ. Caſ. part. 1. c. 23. nu. 1. pag. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>a man may drinke well inough before dinner and after din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as much as hee thinketh good, without any ſinne of not faſting: it is true, that he ſhall ſinne by intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance.</hi> So ſpeaketh <hi>Rodriquez.</hi> And to the like purpoſe <hi>Leſsius;
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ex his infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur primò, Potûs ſumptionem cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briorem non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari; — quare etiam ſi quis eo fine vtatur, eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am immoderatè, non violabit prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptum Eccleſiae de ieiunio, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſi contra temperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam peccet.</hi> Leſ. de Iuſtit. &amp; Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, l. 4. c. 2. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitat. 2. nu. 10. pag. 718.</note> from hence</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it followeth, that often drinking is not forbidden in the time of a Faſt, &amp;c.</hi> — that <hi>although a man doe vſe drinke for that end,</hi> (namely for nouriſhment) <hi>and that immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately, he doth not violate the Churches Precept of faſting, though he ſinne againſt temperance.</hi> And to like purpoſe ſpeake others. So in ſumme their doctrine conſiſteth in two points;</p>
               <p n="1">1. That a man by playing the Glutton or the Drunkard on a faſting day, may ſinne by intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancie or exceſſe, in the like manner as hee ſhould doe on any other day, if he vſed the like exceſſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That no exceſſe in the meaſure either of meate or drinke, is any offence or ſinne againſt the rules of a Romane Faſt: ſo that a man may play both the <hi>glutton</hi> and the <hi>drunkard</hi> vpon a faſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and yet keepe all the rules of a Popiſh Faſt. Only the queſtion further is, Whether a man ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by intemperance in gluttony and drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12743:26"/>and yet at the ſame time keeping their rules of faſting, doe merit at Gods hands by his Faſt? And their anſwer hereto is, That
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Si tantus ſa exceſſus, vt pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet mortiferè, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittit meritum ieiunij, ſicut &amp; aliorum bonorum operum. Si au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem non peccot mortiferè, non amittit abſolutè, ſed ſolum ex par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. Quia qua parte voluntariè abſtinet à cibis vetitis &amp; à ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunde refectione propter Eccleſiae praceplum, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur; quod me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritum non elidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, eliamſi in vſu cibi vel pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tûs non ſeruet debitam modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem: qua ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> parte excedie, non meretur.</hi> Leſſ. de Iuſt. &amp; Iure, l. 4. c. 2. dubitat. 2. nu. 10. p. 718, 719.</note> 
                  <hi>if the exceſſe be ſo great, that it be a deadly or mortall ſinne, then he loſeth the merit of his faſt, as he doth of all other his good workes: but if the man do not ſinne mortally,</hi> (by this exceſſe) <hi>then he doth not abſolutely loſe the merit of his Faſt, but only in part. For in that he doth volun tarily forbeare forbidden meates and a ſecond refecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the Churches commandement, he doth ſo farre forth merit</hi> by his faſting; <hi>which merit is not done away, though he keepe not due moderation in the vſe of meate or drinke: but ſo farre forth as he vſeth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, he doth not merit.</hi> The meaning of which ſpeech is to this purpoſe; that his faſting is a good worke, though at the time of his faſting, hee doe ſurfet and bee drunke: and if his ſurfetting and drunkenneſſe be ſuch and ſo great, that it putteth him out of the ſtate of grace, then he cannot me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit by it, becauſe a man that is not in the ſtate of grace, cannot merit by any worke at all, how good ſoeuer otherwiſe it be: but if his gluttony and exceſſe be not ſuch and ſo great, that it doth exclude him out of the ſtate of grace; then hee meriteth ſtill by his <hi>glutionous</hi> and <hi>drunken</hi> Faſt. And thus ye haue the ſumme of what they ſay in this caſe, concerning the <hi>quantitie</hi> of their <hi>meate</hi> and <hi>drinke</hi> on their faſting dayes: Which is a moſt drunken conceit, and vnworthy the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of learned men or Chriſtians. But the vanity may appeare by theſe conſiderations.</p>
               <p>Firſt, it is againſt the practiſe and opinion of all
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12743:27"/>
                  <hi>Antiquitie.</hi> For their fayings are,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sint tibi quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidiana iciunia, &amp; refectio ſatie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem fugiens. Nibil prodeſt bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duo triduo<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſso, vacuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare ventrem, ſi pariter obruatur, ſi compenſetur ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turitale ieiunium.</hi> Hier. Ep. 22. ad Euſt. pag. 175. B.</note> 
                  <hi>Let thy Faſts be daily, and thy refection without ſatietie. For it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth it nothing to carrie an emptie pauch for two or three dayes together, if at once it bee ouercharged, if the Faſt be recompenced by fulneſse after.</hi> So wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> to <hi>Euſtochium,</hi> giuing her rules of a religious Faſt. And the ſame Father writing to <hi>Ruſticus,</hi> a man that had deuoted himſelfe to a religious life, he giueth him this counſell concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning faſting;
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quae &amp; ipſa (ielunia) mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rata ſint, ne nimia debilitent ſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; maiorem refectionem poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia, erumpant in cruditatem, quae parens libi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinum eſt. Modi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus ac temperatus cibus, &amp; carni &amp; animae vtilis eſt.</hi> Hier. Ep. 4. ad Ruſtic. pa. 43. A.</note> 
                  <hi>Let Faſts be moderate; leſt being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate, they weaken the ſtomacke, and requiring greater refection afterward, they breake out into cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity and inconcoction, which is the mother of luſt. Sparing and temperate diet is good both for body and ſoule.</hi> And yet againe the ſame Father,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Nonnulli vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam pudicam ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petentium, in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio itinere corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, dum ſolam abſtinentiam car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium putant, &amp; leguminibus one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ſtomachum, quae moderatè parcéque ſumpta innoxia ſunt. Et, vt quod ſentio loquar, nihil ſic inſlammat corpora &amp; litillat membra genitalia, ſicut indigeſtus cibus, ructuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> convulſus. — Parcus cibus &amp; venter ſemper eſuriens triduanis ieiunijs praefertur.</hi> Hieron. Ep. 10. ad Furiam, pag. 93. D. E.</note> 
                  <hi>Many</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>who doe deſire a chaſte life, doe fall in the mid-way, while they thinke that abſtinence is onely in forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of fleſh, and fill the belly with pulſe, which being taken moderately and ſparingly is without harme. And to ſpeake what I thinke,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>nothing doth ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame mens bodies, and ſtirre vp luſt, as vndigeſted meat.</hi> He yet addeth, <hi>Sparing diet, and a ſtomack ſtill hungrie, is better then Faſts three dayes long.</hi> From which ſpeeches of this learned and religious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, any man may collect, that if hee thought a full meale after immoderate abſtinence would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gender luſt, then ſure he neuer could imagine, that ſurfetting on a faſting day can bee a meanes to coole luſt, and to beate downe the body. And if
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12743:27"/>he thought, that it was in vaine and without profit, to faſt much, if a man did make amends for his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence by fulneſſe afterward; then certainely he would neuer yeeld, that men did a meritorious worke, if abſtaining from fleſh, they did on the very day loade themſelues with exceſſe of any meates and drinkes. But to proceed, <hi>Caſsian</hi> ſaith, that
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Non qualitas ſola, ſed etiam quantitas eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum aciem cordis obtundit, ac men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te cum corne pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riter impinguatae noxium vitiorum fomitem igneum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſuccendit.</hi> Caſſian. Inſt. l. 5. c. 5. pag. 195</note> 
                  <hi>not onely the qualitie of meates, but the quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie alſo, doth blunt the edge or vigor of the heart, and fatting the minde with the body, it doth kindle a nox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ious and firie fuell of vices.</hi> And a little after he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſculentiores cibi, vt procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant corporis ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatem, ita caſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis non adimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t puritatem, ſi cum moderatione ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantur.</hi> Caſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. ibid. cap. 7. pag. 198.</note> 
                  <hi>that the more nouriſhing meates, as they breed health to the body, ſo they doe not take away the purity of chaſtitie, if they be taken moderately.</hi> By which ſpeeches we ſee, that this ancient Father is ſo far from allowing exceſſe in a Faſt, that he preferreth a ſparing meale of the beſt meates, before a full meale of the courſeſt: as alſo in the former reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of St. <hi>Hierome</hi> we may obſerue, that that Father preferreth a moderate refection of fleſh, before a plentifull refection of pulſe; and (as if he had meant to reproue the error of the preſent Roman Churth) he derideth them who thinke to preſerue chaſtitie, while they abſtaine from fleſh, and fill themſelues with pulſe. To the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it is, that
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Malunt bi, qui perfectionem diſcretionis igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, etiam bidus protelare ieiunia, idque quod hodie ſumpluri fuer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t, in craſtinum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re: dum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo ad refecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem peruenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, deſideratâ ſatietate potian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur. Quod nuper Benia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min ciuem veſtrum pertina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer tenuiſſe cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcitis, qui ne quotidiè paximacia duo percipiens, aequali caſtigatione continuam parcitatem iugiter retentaret, maluit biduana ieiunia ſemper continuare, dummode ad refectionem veniens, duplicatâ menſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rârepleret ventris ingluviem, &amp;c.</hi> Caſſian. Collat, 2. c. 24. pag. 125.</note> 
                  <hi>Caſsian</hi> telleth vs of a young Monke named <hi>Beniamin,</hi> who after his daies faſt, finding his euening refection to be farre ſhort of ſatisfying his hunger, deſired to faſt two daies together,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12743:28"/>without any thing at all: ſo that at the end of the ſecond day he might haue his allowance for the two dayes together, and ſo ſatisfie his hunger for the time. But the religious Fathers of that time would not conſent vnto it. And <hi>Caſsian</hi> ſetteth vs downe this fact of <hi>Beniamin,</hi> as an example of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcretion, which he warneth all wiſe Chriſtians to beware of. Thus farre were theſe truely-reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Fathers from giuing way to this gluttonous feeding, and intemperate drinking, now allowed in the Church of Rome to conſiſt with the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruance of an holy Faſt.</p>
               <p>Secondly, this exceſſiue quantitie of meate and drinke on a faſting day, is againſt the nature and vſe of a Faſt, and the <hi>deſcription</hi> which they of the Romane Church doe giue of it. For, (as hath beene declared already out of <hi>Valentia</hi>) one <hi>eſsen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall</hi> thing in a religious faſt is this, that the abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence then vſed, be ordained to the <hi>taming</hi> of the fleſh, and <hi>bridling</hi> of concupiſcence. But he that drinketh wine to the full all day, and feedeth at noone by the belly, and eateth as much as might ſuffice three moderate men, doth <hi>afftict</hi> the body but a little: ſuch a one, I ſuppoſe, might goe ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perleſſe to bed, and feele no hunger, though hee did forbeare his <hi>euening Collation.</hi> And vpon this ground (as I conceiue) one of their owne faith,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Poſtremum, à quo abſtinere iubent Canones ſunt cibi delicati — ſum cibi multi, licèt ſemel ſumpti. Scio quid hac de re dicant multi, qui ad noſtros m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>res tolerandos, quam ad vele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem diſciplinam exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>candam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiùs loquuntur: tamen, ſi quod res eſt, licet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteri, qui poſſit dic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ieiunus, qui non ſit tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, non equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem intelligo: tam non, quàm non id eſſe homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, quod ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal non ſit.</hi> Ant. Liturg. to. 1. ferin quartâ quatuor tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum, p. 105.</note> that one thing which the Canons of the Church did forbid, was <hi>[<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ibi multi, licèt ſemel ſumpti,] much meate, or many meates, though but taken once in the day.</hi> He addeth, that notwithſtanding this exceſſiue eating haue his patrones among them,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:12743:28"/>yet (faith he) <hi>If I may profeſſe that which is the truth, I cannot tell how he may be ſaid to be faſting, that is not temperate; no more then how he can be a man, that is not a liuing creature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this ſhall ſerue for the fourth particular.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI. </hi>Diſpenſations in the Roman Church, againſt the rules offaſting.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He laſt is their <hi>Diſpenſations;</hi> and they bee of two ſorts: ſome are <hi>explicite,</hi> and others are <hi>implicite.</hi> The <hi>explicite</hi> or expreſſe Diſpenſations are, when the Pope or other Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates doe by word or writing, giue leaue or licenſe to ſome men, not to obſerue their rules of faſting; as for example, when they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe with men to eate cheeſe &amp; eggs in Lent; or ſuch like. Their <hi>implicite</hi> Diſpenſations are, when the people take libertie in their practice againſt the rules or precepts of the Church, and their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops or Prelates ſeeing it, ſay nothing to the contrarie, but wincke at it: for this <hi>conniuence</hi> in the Prelates, eſpecially in the Pope, they hold as good as an expreſſe Diſpenſation. Now concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning theſe two kindes of <hi>Diſpenſations,</hi> wee are to conſider 2. things 11. What power they are of in the Romane Church to diſſolue the rules of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12743:29"/>and 2. What way is giuen to them in the practiſe of that Church.</p>
               <p>And firſt, for their <hi>expreſſe Diſpenſations,</hi> they ſay,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Summus Pontifex poteſt diſpenſare in prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepto ieiunij, quomuis fuit ab Apoſtolis inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum. Ratio eſt; quia in hac lege ferenda Apoſtoli vſi fuere poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te gubernandi ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi à Chriſto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſâ; &amp; in ijs quae periment ad gubernationem Eccleſiae ſummus Pontifex habet aequalem poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, ſicut Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoli babuerunt.</hi> Ioſ. Angels in 4. de Ieiunio. q. 5. diffic. 2. concl. 1 p. 394. v. Ioh. Medin. in Cod. de Ieiunio. q. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>that the Pope may diſpenſe in the Precept of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, although it were made by the Apoſtles. The reaſon is, becauſe in making of this Law, the Apoſtles vſed the power of gouernment, which Chriſt did grant them; and in thoſe things, which pertaine to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the Church, the Pope hath as much power as the Apoſtles had.</hi> They ſay alſo, that the
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dicò primò Papam poſſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſare quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque etiam per tolam vitam. Communis Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum in Rubri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis de obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one ieiunij, Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt. Ieiun.</hi> 47. <hi>Nauar. nu.</hi> 21. <hi>Eſt enim ſupra hoc praeceptu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſit tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de iure canonico; vude etiam ſine cauſa valida eſſet diſpenſatio.</hi> Fill. tract. 27. pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. 2. c. 6 nu. 126. pa. 290.</note> 
                  <hi>Pope may diſpenſe with a man for his whole life. For hee is aboue this Law of Faſts, ſeeing it is onely enioyned by the Canon Law
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ibid. nu. 127.</note>: and from hence it followeth alſo, that his Diſpenſation is good, though it be granted without cauſe.</hi> And for inferior Biſhops and Prelates, they may diſpenſe with thoſe which are vnder them, vpon iuſt cauſe, &amp;c. <hi>Bartholomew Medina</hi> ſaith,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do habet quis iuſtè aut iniuſlè di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non iciunandi, non tenetur; quamuis peccaret huiuſmodi diſpenſatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſine occaſione pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendo: at ſi eam obtinuerit, valida crit. Ratio eſt: nam quu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> humana ſit lex iſta, poteſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>amſilmus Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifex aut alius toll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re.</hi> Barth. Med. Inſt. Conf. l. 1. c. 14. §. 10. p. 150.</note> 
                  <hi>that when a man hath a Diſpenſation for not faſting, whether iuſtly or vniuſtly, he is not tyed to the Law; though he ſinned in asking ſuch a Diſpenſation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe. But if hee obtaine it, the Diſpenſation is good. For ſeeing that Law is onely poſitiue, and of mans making, the Pope or an other Biſhop may diſsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>null it.</hi> So, their expreſſe Diſpenſations are <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent</hi> againſt all Laws of faſting. And the like they ſay in a manner for their <hi>implicite</hi> Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or the conniuence of the Pope and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates at the peoples practiſe. For,
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuetudo Tinelli Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manae Curiae in omnibus ieiunys no improbatur à Caietan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> Fil. Tra. 27. par. 2. c. 2. nu. 34. p. 280.</note> 
                  <hi>the cuſtome v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:12743:29"/>in the Popes Court on faſting dayes, is, not to be diſallowed in any thing, as Caietan ſaith.</hi> The like they ſay of cuſtomes in other places alſo.
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vt conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do priorem legis obligationem tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat, non opus eſt vt ſit rationabilis &amp; praeſcripta; ſed ſatis eſt, ſi per tantum tempus ſit buiuſmodi conſuetudo indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta &amp; obſeruata, vt ad notitiam Maiorum perue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerit, qui quum cam ſciant, mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè contradicunt, quum commode ſi vellent, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicere poſſent, &amp; prauaricatores punire, &amp;c.</hi> Io. Medina Cod. de Ieiun. q. 8. pag. 347.</note> 
                  <hi>Nor is it needfull</hi> in this caſe, <hi>that the cuſtome be reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and by preſcription; it is ſufficient, if it haue bin kept ſo long, that it doe come to the knowledge of Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, who when they know it, do not contradict or gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay it, when they might conueniently gaineſay it if they would.</hi> They be the words of <hi>Medina,</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed vnto by
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Prax. fori Poenitent l 4. nu. 134. p. 148, 149.</note> 
                  <hi>Ioſephus Angles,</hi> that he hath tranſcribed them out of him word for word, and publiſhed them for his owne. By this it may bee ſeene, what power they place in their Diſpenſations, whether they be giuen by expreſſe words, or only brought in by the <hi>cuſtome</hi> of the people, and the <hi>conniuence</hi> of the Biſhops.</p>
               <p>And all this were not ſo great a matter; if Pope and Prelates were warie in granting Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and winking at licencious cuſtomes. But it is farre otherwiſe. For
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Fuit prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptum de abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netia à carnibus, primùm Clericis impoſitum, dein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ad fideles om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes fuit diffuſum: in omni autem loco cibus quadrageſimalis intelligitur abſque ouis &amp; lacticinijs. Iam verò eſt communiſſima diſpenſatio, quam qui obtinuerunt, ſine ſcrupulo poſſunt vti praemiſſis.</hi> Ioſeph. Angles in 4. de Ieiunio. q. 9. difficult. 2. concl. 4. pag. 424.</note> 
                  <hi>a Diſpenſation againſt the rules of Lent is moſt common; which he that hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, may without ſcruple of conſcience vſe the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes;</hi> that is, he may eate <hi>fleſh and white meates.</hi> And
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Papa in Bullis ſuis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedit puſſim facul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>atem comedendi oua, caſeum &amp; lac in Quadrageſima, &amp; carnem ex ſolo me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dici conſilio, &amp; parum deeſt, quin generaliter cum omnibus diſpenſet, vt ieiunent carnes come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendo; ſicut dicitur cum multis Nobilibus diſpenſaſſe.</hi> Ioh. Med. Cod. de Ieiun. q. 2. pa. 328.</note> 
                  <hi>the Pope</hi> (ſaith <hi>Medina) doth euery where in his Buls grant licence to cate eggs, cheeſe and milke in Lent time, yea and fleſh too, by the alone aduice of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12743:30"/>a Phyſician: and there wanteth but a little of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſing generally with all men, that they may faſt with eating of fleſh, as it is ſaid that he hath diſpenſed with many Noble-men.</hi> And <hi>Beyerlinck</hi> ſhewing the eaſineſſe of a Romane Faſt now-a-dayes, ouer that it was in time paſt, ſaith, that
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eteres Chriſtiani quoad hanc ieiunandi legem admodum rigidi, pauciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s ab illius ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruatione exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mebant. Nunc infiniti aut imbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillitatis aut ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitatis titulo hac obligatione liberantur.</hi> Bey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. in feſto Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um, tex. 3. in fine pag. 64.</note> 
                  <hi>the ancient Chriſtians being very ſtrict and rigid about this Law of faſting, did releaſe very few from the obſeruation and keeping of it: but now an infinite number, vpon pretence either of weakeneſſe or neceſsity, are freed from the bond of it.</hi> So they are very liberal of their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations, &amp; that not only in ordinarie Faſts, and at common times; but euen in the holy and ſtrict time of Lent. Nor haue theſe Diſpenſations gone ſo farre, but their cuſtomes, by which the rules of abſtinence are abrogated, haue extended much further. For,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Conſuetudo abrogauit ieiuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Rogationum, quod praecipitur in Cap. Rogatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes de Conſecrat. Diſt.</hi> 3. <hi>Item ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunium quartae &amp; ſextae feriae, iam inde ab Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolorum tempori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus in praecepto poſitum, conſtat conſuetudine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brogatum eſſe, &amp; arbitrio noſtro relictum. — De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ieiunium Aduentus, aliàs ſolitum ſeruari in Eccleſia Romana — contraria conſueludo iam ſuſtulit.</hi> Reginald. Prax. l. 4. nu. 133. pag 148.</note> 
                  <hi>cuſtome</hi> [not controled by the Prelates] <hi>hath abrogated the Faſt of the Rogation weeke, which was commanded by the Canon Law: as alſo the Wedneſday and Fryday Faſt, which, as they ſay, was enioyned by Precept euer ſince the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles time:</hi> and ſo likewiſe <hi>it hath taken away the Faſt of Aduent, which otherwiſe was vſed to bee kept in the Romane Church by vertue of the Canon.</hi> And cuſtome
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hinc excuſantur a Doctoribus, qui iuxta morem &amp; conſuetudinem patriae, in die ieiunij longiores Collationes faciunt, &amp;c. Hinc etiam Mediolanenſes excuſantur, non ieiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantes primis quatuer diebus Quadrageſimae. — Hine etiam excuſantur ante horam veſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum manducantes. — Hire Britones excuſantur, qui in Quadrageſima butyro vtuntur, vbi talis viget conſuetudo, aut ouis, aliſſque ex carne originem trabentibus, quum contrarium ſit iure definitum. Hinc à peccato liberantur comedentes carnes in aliquibus locis in die Sabbathi.</hi> Ioſeph. Angles in 4. de Ieiun q. 5. Diffic. 1. pag. 393. Who hath tranſcribed Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina. Cod. de Ieiun. q. 8. pag. 346.</note> it is that brought in <hi>long Collations
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:12743:30"/>at night,</hi> and made them lawfull: and cuſtome <hi>that excuſeth the inhabitants of Milane, for not fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting the foure firſt daies in Lent: and that excuſeth men for eating their Supper before Euen ſong:</hi> and cuſtome that <hi>excuſeth the Britons for eating of but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the Lent time, where that cuſtome is on foote, or eggs and other things which come of fleſh.</hi> And fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, cuſtome hath made it lawfull to eate before noone on a faſting day, to vſe a groſſe Collatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on Chriſtmas Eue, as before I ſhewed: as alſo,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>In noſtra Hispania, -inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luit conſuetudo maiori ex parte, vt comedantur in Sabbatho omnia interiora anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium &amp; extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, vt pedes &amp; capita, &amp; omnia lardaſagimina, etiam porcinum craſſum, &amp;c.</hi> Llamas part. 3. c. 5. §. vlt. pa. 399.</note> 
                  <hi>on Saturday to eat the entrales of beaſts, with their heads and feete, and beſides, bacon and ſwines fleſh alſo:</hi> Yea,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Statutum de abſtinendo à carnibus in domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicis diebus Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drageſime olim obligatoriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, quia non fuit vtentium mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus approbatum, vt ait Greg. in Epiſt. ad Epiſcop. Anglorum.</hi> Ioh. Medina. Cod. de Ieiun. q. 8. p. 346. Col. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>to eate fleſh on Sundaies in Lent,</hi> contrarie to the Law, where the vſe of men was to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie. Thus, and in this manner cuſtome with them hath preuailed, to the abrogating both of the ancient Laws, and their owne rules: and to the bringing in and iuſtifying of ſtrange libertie, contrarie to the practice of Gods ancient people, and the deſcriptions of faſting approued by the Church of Rome. And how farre further it may grow, we could not imagine, ſauing that wee ſee there is little or nothing in a manner left, that is worth the <hi>diſpenſing</hi> with. For what with their doctrine, and what with their Diſpenſations and cuſtomes, faſting with them is become ſo eaſie and pleaſant a courſe, that an <hi>Epicure</hi> may ſatisfie his voluptuous appetite, and yet keepe a Romane Faſt.</p>
               <p>And this may ſuffice for manifeſting their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence</hi> and licenciouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>Out of all which, we may further deduce and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12743:31"/>obſerue theſe <hi>Collections</hi> following.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Faſt, in moſt points of moment, is moſt vnlike to the <hi>ancient</hi> Faſts. For the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients</hi> abſtained from <hi>Wine,</hi> and <hi>Spices,</hi> and <hi>Iun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates;</hi> the <hi>Papiſts</hi> allow theſe, as moſt innocent on a faſting day. The <hi>Ancients</hi> had one only refection in the day of their Faſt; the <hi>Papiſts</hi> haue two or three, or more; for the all dayes <hi>drinking</hi> is more then one refection. The <hi>Ancients</hi> did faſt till e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening, or when zeale was ſomewhat decayed, till three of the clocke at leaſt; the <hi>Papiſts</hi> breake off their Faſts at noone, or an houre or two ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. The <hi>Ancients</hi> were ſparing in their one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and fed on courſe fare; the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in their ſet refection feede by the bellie, and chooſe ſuch meates and ſawces as beſt pleaſe the appetite, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided onely that they eate not fleſh. And finally, the <hi>Ancients</hi> were ſtrict and rigid obſeruers of their rules and orders of faſting; the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are moſt looſe in diſpenſing with all men, and in all things that haue any ſhew of hardneſſe or afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in them. Theſe contrarieties betweene our new Doctors and the old Fathers, I haue proued alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as I paſſed thorow the Particulars: but if any man deſire to ſee them all together in one heape, he may finde them collected and acknowledged by the friends and wel-willers of the Church of Rome: who reckon vp theſe, not to their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhame, but for the praiſe of her loue and tenderneſſe to her children, whom ſhe would not chaſten ſo ſeuerely, as the old Church of Chriſt was wont to chaſten her children. <hi>Piſanuc</hi> then
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:12743:31"/>the Ieſuite, thus commendeth the tender loue of the Romane Church to her babes and ſucklings.
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Si qua in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſciplina Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtica laxata &amp; &amp; lapſa eſt, id maximè in ieiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niorum ratione videre licet, ac ex huius lectione libelli fatis ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maduertetur. Sanè pia mater Eccleſia, imbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillitati noſtrae ſe accommodat, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius proinde pieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem commendare debemus. — Ad Veterem &amp; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicam Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiam plerique om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes prouocant, ſed huius ieiunia ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta &amp; ſolennia vel non probant, vel ne per ſomni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um quidem ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur.</hi> Piſan. Praefat. ad Lector. prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixâ libro de Abſtinent. pag. 96, 97.</note> 
                  <hi>If</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Diſcipline of the Church bee any where relaxed and falne downe, it is moſt of all to be ſeene in the matter of Faſts, and may bee well inough perceiued by the reading of this booke. Forſooth, our holy Mother the Church doth apply her ſelfe to our weakenes, whoſe motherly care we ought therefore to commend.</hi> And againe; <hi>All men for the moſt part, doe appeale to the ancient and Apoſtolike Church: but her ſet and ſolemne Faſts they either doe not allow, or doe neuer a whit follow her in them.</hi> And the ſame Author,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Non eſt—quòd aliquis ieiunij difficultate deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reatur. Siquidem tanta moderatio eſt adhibita, per Eccleſiae praxin, antiquorum Canonum perfectioni, vt qui hodie ſciens praeceptum abſque neceſſitate ieiunium negligit, non leue profectò cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men incurrat. Ecce enim veteres Canones non ſolùm vin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m, ſed etiam ſiceram interdixére, &amp; omne quod inebriare poteſt, &amp; mulſam ac ceruiſiam. Olera tantùm concedebant in eſum, ſecluſit etiam ipſis piſcibus, &amp;c. Hodiè &amp; vino &amp; piſcibus vti licet. Nec ampliùs, vt olim, ſemel tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum veſperi reficimur; ſed coenae in prandia ſunt commutatae, &amp;c. Quid? quòd à quibuſdam terrae fructibus abſtinebant olim Catholici in Quadrageſuna (vt docuit Auguſtinus contra Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum) nempe ab aromatis, aut ijs quae Venerem excitant, iuxta praeceptum Apoſtolerum, ſola Olera admittentium: in quo etiam Eccleſia Catholica poteſtatem habens Apoſtolicam, vt &amp; in alijs multis benignè nobiſcum dispenſauit, &amp;c. Poſtremò, quia Canones ieiunantibus cibum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibent, potum non prohibent; ſubingreſſae ſunt, conuiuentibus Hierarchis, noſtrae nocturnae Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiunculae, Veteribus prorſus ignotae, eo videlicet praetextu, ne potus noceat, &amp;c.</hi> Piſan. de Abſtinent. cap. 14. pag. 162, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>There is no cauſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>why any man ſhould be deterred with the difficultie of faſting. For the practice of the Church hath ſo moderated and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigated the perfection of the old Canons, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer now doth wittingly neglect the Faſt that is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red without neceſsity, out of doubt he ſhall incurre no ſmall crime.</hi> Yea, but what is that mitigation, which the Church hath vſed in tempering the old Canons? Hee goeth on to tell vs that in theſe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:12743:32"/>words: <hi>Behold,</hi> (ſaith he, and ſure the thing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth attention) <hi>the old Canons did not only forbid wine, but all ſtrong drinke that might trouble the braine, and Meath, and Ale or Beere: they allowed onely hearbs to be eaten on their faſting dayes, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding euen fiſh alſo, &amp;c. But now-a-dayes, wee may lawfully vſe both fiſh and wine. Nor do we any longer, as aforetime they were wont, refreſh our ſelues once onely in the euening; but ſuppers are turned with vs into dinners, &amp;c. Nay, the Catholikes of ancient time did in Lent abſtaine from ſome fruites of the earth, (as Auguſtine teacheth againſt Faustus) namely from ſpices, and ſuch things as ſtirre vp luſt, according to the precept of the Apoſtles, who admit hearbs alone: wherein, as in many other things, the Catholike Church, hauing Apoſtolike authoritie, hath fauour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably diſpenſed with vs, &amp;c. Laſtly, becauſe the Churches Canons doe forbid meate, but not drinke; our euening Refections, vnknowne to the Ancients, haue, by the conniuencie of the Prelates, priuily crept in; vpon pretence, forſooth, leſt drinke alone ſhould doe harme.</hi> Thus he: and in like ſort another:
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quantum de prima illa Veterum ieiuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum ſeueritate bact<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nus detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum eſt? Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iores noſtri feria 4, 6. &amp; pleri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que etiam Sabbatho, non ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum carnibus ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlinebant, ſed eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ieiunabant: nunc feriam ſex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam &amp; Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thum in Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicae paſſionis &amp; mortis memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, delectu tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tùm ciborum ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebramus. Illi ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunijs adiunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant vigilias, &amp; nocturnos ad o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum deum agebant conuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus: nos vnius exiguum speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men retinuimus, ſcilicet, Natiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis Domini. Jlli in horam nonam, imo vſque ad veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peram ieiunia ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendebant, nec prandere, ſed canare ſoliti: nos cadem ſtatim in meridie relaxamus, &amp; prandia ſumimus, ea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que talia, vt praeteritam abſtinentiam copiâ &amp; varietate ciborum facilè compenſemus. Illi vnicam refeetiunculam, eámque ten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>em ieiunantibus indulgebant: nos longo &amp; pleno prandio vespertinam adijcimus refectiunculam, quae ſaepenumerè in coenam degeneret. Abſtinebant illi etiam piſcibue, omnique potu, qui inebriare poteſt: nunc in ſolis carnibus ciborum delectus ferè conſiſtit. Denique veteres Chriſtiani, quoad hanc ieiunandi legem admodum rigidi, pauciſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> os ab illius obſeruatione eximebant: nunc infiniti, aut imbecillitatis aut neceſſitatis titulo bac ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l'gatione l'berantur.</hi> Laurent. Beyerl. prompt moral. part. 3. in feſto Cinerum, tex. 3. pag. 63, 64.</note> 
                  <hi>How much</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hath hitherto beene abated of the former ſeueritie of the ancient Faſts? Our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, on Wedneſday, Friday, and moſt of them on
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:12743:32"/>Saturday alſo, did not onely abſtaine from fleſh meates, but did alſo faſt: but now we keepe Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day and Saturday for the memory of Chriſts Paſsion and death, only with forbearing ſome meates,</hi> [with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermitting any meale.] <hi>They to their faſtings ioyned watchings, and had night-aſſemblies for pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er vnto God; we haue onely kept a little ſemblance of one of them, namely of Chriſtmaſſe Eue. They conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued their Faſts till three of the clocke, yea till euen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; nor were they wonted to dine, but to ſup: we breake off our Faſts at mid-day, and take our dinners, and them ſuch, that we doe eaſily recompence the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going abſtinence with plentie and varietie of meates. They allowed but one onely Refection, and that a ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one: we to a long and full Dinner, doe adde an euening Refection, which many times doth degenerate into a Supper. They abſtained from fiſh, and all drinke that may intoxicate the braine: now our choiſe of meates conſiſteth for the moſt part in the forbearing of fleſh alone. Finally, the ancient Chriſtians, being very ſtrict about the rules of faſting, did exempt very few fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the obſeruance thereof: but now the number is infinite of them, that vpon pretence of weaknes or neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie are freed from this bond.</hi> And from all this hee inferreth,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vnde quum dominum habea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus tam manſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etum, Eccleſiam matrem tam be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignam, quae in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitatibus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris condolere non negligit, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilque quod ſupra vires ſit, exigal: exhibeamus nos etiam dicto eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum audientes, &amp;c.</hi> Beyer. l. c.</note> 
                  <hi>that ſeeing we haue ſo milde a Lord,</hi> (I ſuppoſe he meaneth the Pope) <hi>and ſo tender a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Church, which is not backward to condole our infirmities, and requireth nothing of vs aboue our ſtrength; let vs yeeld our ſelues obedient to their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, &amp;c.</hi> And ſurely, he that will not yeeld to ſo eaſie a penance, deſerueth to pay for it in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie. But the thing that I intend in tranſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:12743:33"/>theſe two Authors, is, at one view to let the world ſee, how much the Church of Rome, euen by the confeſſion of her owne flatterers, is dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated from the practice of the <hi>Primitiue</hi> and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer Church. And therefore when they alledge vnto vs the ſayings and doings of Fathers and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Writers, for defence and commendation of their Faſts, they doe therein play the Gibeonites with vs. They tel vs of old faſting daies aforetime, of choiſe of meates vſed in the Primitiue Church, and what account the Fathers made of the Faſt of Lent; but when they put theſe names vpon their owne Faſts, they ſhew vs but their owne worne <hi>raggs</hi> and <hi>broken bottles,</hi> and <hi>clowted ſhooes,</hi> which they would make vs beleeue came afarre off, euen from the firſt times of the Primitiue Church: and if we will beleeue them vpon their owne word, as the Iſraelites beleeued the ſmooth tale of the Gibeonites, then we may be deceiued by theſe Iebuſites, as they were by thoſe Gibeonites. But if we aske counſell at the mouth of the Lord, or if we aduiſe with the ancient Fathers of the Church, we ſhall finde that all this ſtuffe is but counterfeit traſh; no more like to the Faſts of the Prophets, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, ancient Fathers and Chriſtians of former times, then an Ape is like to a man.</p>
               <p>Secondly, We may note out of the former paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, that they know not how to define a Faſt, but ſo, as that they muſt withall contradict their owne rules, and condemne their owne practice. For in their <hi>definition</hi> of a Faſt, they ſay, that it is a <hi>ſtraiter abſtinence</hi> then the rules of Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:12743:33"/>doe require: and yet by their rules a man may eate and drinke exceſſiuely, without breaking of a Roman Faſt. They ſay in their <hi>definition,</hi> that in a Faſt there muſt bee but <hi>one Refection;</hi> and yet by their rules, a man may eate a full Dinner, and a little Collation, which proueth a iuſt ſupper, and drinke what he will all day long. They ſay in the <hi>definition,</hi> that a Faſt is a <hi>longer abſtinence</hi> then ordinarie, and that the time of refection then muſt be later: and yet by their rules a man may take his meale at twelue, eleuen, or tenne of the clocke; which is, I thinke, as ſoone as any man vſeth to dine on ordinarie dayes. And laſtly, in the <hi>definition</hi> they ſay, that a Faſt, both for the <hi>continuance</hi> of the abſtinence, and for the <hi>qualitie</hi> of the meate when the abſtinence is ended, muſt be ſuch as may <hi>beat downe</hi> the body, <hi>tame</hi> the fleſh, and bridle concupiſcence; and yet by their rules, a man may eat &amp; drink ſo much and ſo often, as will breede no affliction to any man liuing. Thus their doctrine is croſſed by their owne <hi>definition.</hi> Nor could it well bee otherwiſe. For both their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in the particulars, and their practice in the vſe of a Faſt is ſuch, as that if they had framed a generall <hi>definition</hi> of a Faſt, that had bin agreeable thereunto, it would plainely haue appeared, that they had bidden open defiance to all Antiquitie, yea, and to their elder Schoolemen too. And therefore they thought it better in generall to profeſſe conformitie to Scriptures and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Church, and in particular ſo to molde it by diſtinctions and conſiderations and congruities
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:12743:34"/>of a reaſonable alteration, as might ſerue to bleare their eyes that are wilfully blinde. But a wiſe man, who hath his eyes in his head, will eaſily ſee the diſproportion betweene their generall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition and their particular doctrines.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, we may gather from the premiſes, that the religious Faſts of Rome are nothing but a ſuperſtitious fopperie; and a meere mocking both of God and men. For all is but an out-ſide, there is no pith nor vertue within: a Faſt in name, but in deede nothing leſſe. I ſhall not neede to declare this further in this place; it is ſufficiently demonſtrated already: and if neede be, we haue the witneſſe of one of their owne Prophets, who confeſſeth in a manner as much as I haue ſaid. For,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Et ſanè non multùm ieiunat, qui in diebus ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuniorum non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rctiùs ieiunat, quàm Eccleſia iubet; hoc eſt, qui edit &amp; bibit omnia quae Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia permittit, vel quae non pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit.</hi> Lorich. Theſaur. v. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iun. nu. 10. pag. 1130.</note> 
                  <hi>to ſay the truth,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>he faſteth not much, who on faſting dayes faſteth not more ſtraitely then the Church doth command: that is, who eateth and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth al things which the Church doth permit, or which it doth not puniſh.</hi> By which laſt words, added (as I conceiue) by ſome Cenſor before hee licenſed the Booke to the Preſſe; though he mayſeeme to ſup vp againe his owne breath, and onely to ſay, that the Church doth tolerate theſe things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giuing allowance to them: yet this qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will not helpe the matter. For whatſoeuer they ſuffer to goe vncontrolled, that they allow as lawfull and without fault; as hath alreadie bin declared. But <hi>Lindan</hi> is plaine, and ſpeaketh home, when he calleth their Faſts <hi>[Ieiunia Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea,]</hi> Epicures Faſts. And indeed they haue more affinity with the feeding of an Epicure, then with
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:12743:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>the faſting of a deuout Chriſtian. In reſpect of all which, as our Sauiour ſaid to his Diſciples, <hi>When ye faſt, be not as the Hypocrites, of a ſad counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, &amp;c,</hi> ſo let me ſay to all ſincere Chriſtians, When ye faſt, be not as <hi>theſe Hypocrites,</hi> al for ſhew and nothing for ſubſtance. But when ye faſt, vſe a true abſtinence, ſuch as may <hi>afflict</hi> the body, <hi>maſter</hi> the fleſh, <hi>eleuate</hi> the ſoule, and <hi>humble</hi> the whole man by repentance and ſorrow: and toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with outward abſtinence ioyne inward ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of deuotion, examining your conſciences, acknowledging your ſins, condemning your own ſelues, as vnworthy to taſte of any of Gods crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and running to the Throne of grace for mercie and forgiueneſſe: that your ſinnes beeing pardoned, your conſciences may bee comforted, and your ſoules better enabled for Gods ſeruice.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, we may gather, what a ſmooth and eaſie way the Church of Rome doth paue for men vnto heauen and happineſſe. For theſe looſe and licencious Faſts of theirs, they ſay that they haue great power both to <hi>merit</hi> heauen, and to free a man from <hi>Purgatorie.</hi> But if they can merit and ſatisfie in this manner, and by this meanes; they may with much eaſe haue many merits, and great ſtore of ſatisfactions: nor is it any wonder that they talke of ſuch a multitude of theſe things laid vp in the Churches Treaſurie. It is a wonder ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if the Treaſurie of the Church bee not long ſince ſo full, that they want ſoules to beſtow them vpon. Yea, and a wonder it may well ſeeme, if on the other ſide, there be any man ſo careleſſe of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:12743:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>himſelfe, as to ſtand in need of them. For he that for his ſoules health will not faſt (as they call faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nig) ſo often and ſo much as they doe require, is a moſt negligent man of his ſaluation; and it is pitty that euer he ſhould goe to heauen, or be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from Purgatorie or hell. But thoſe who heare Chriſt ſay, and conſider what he meaneth, when he ſaith, <hi>Striue to enter in at the ſtrait gate;</hi> cannot thinke to buy heauen at ſo eaſie a rate, nor to make ſatisfaction for their ſins with ſo ſleight a <hi>penance.</hi> They will thinke all little enough, though with <hi>Dauid,</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Ezrah,</hi> they <hi>chaſten</hi> and <hi>afflict</hi> their ſoules with faſting. Nor will they thinke when all is done, to merit hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, or to ſatisfie Gods Iuſtice by it. Let Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts preach their merits while they will, true Chriſtians wil be both more penitent, and leſſe proud.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAg. 9. in marg. lit. c. Bellar. — pag. 168, 169, r. pag. 1068, 1069. Pag. 10. in marg. lit. a. <hi>diſtoſitionem &amp; ciborum digeſtionem.</hi> r. <hi>dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitionem &amp; digeſtionem.</hi> Pag. 14. in marg. lit. a. <hi>flammas.</hi> r. <hi>flammas.</hi> Pag. 25. in marg. lit. c. adde in the end, Filliuc. Tract. 27. part. 2. c. 2. num. 42. pag. 281. Pag. 28. in marg. lit. c. <hi>ſoluant.</hi> r. <hi>ſoluunt.</hi> Pag. 35. in marg. lin. vlt. <hi>prandedi.</hi> r. <hi>prandendi.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12743:35"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
